<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The anatomyes of the true physition, and counterfeit mounte-banke wherein both of them, are graphically described, and set out in their right, and orient colours. Published in Latin by Iohn Oberndorff, a learned German: and translated into English by F.H. fellow of the Coll. of Physitions in London. Hereunto is annexed: A short discourse, or, Discouery of certaine stratagems, whereby our London-empericks, haue bene obserued strongly to oppugne, and oft times to expugne their poore patients purses.</title>
            <title>De veri et falsi medici cognitione. English</title>
            <author>Oberndorf, Johann.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120711</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855905</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855905</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21413</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08437)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21413)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 997:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The anatomyes of the true physition, and counterfeit mounte-banke wherein both of them, are graphically described, and set out in their right, and orient colours. Published in Latin by Iohn Oberndorff, a learned German: and translated into English by F.H. fellow of the Coll. of Physitions in London. Hereunto is annexed: A short discourse, or, Discouery of certaine stratagems, whereby our London-empericks, haue bene obserued strongly to oppugne, and oft times to expugne their poore patients purses.</title>
                  <title>De veri et falsi medici cognitione. English</title>
                  <author>Oberndorf, Johann.</author>
                  <author>Herring, Francis, d. 1628.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [By T. Creede] for Arthur Iohnson, and are to be sold at his shop in Powles Church-yard, at the signe of the Flower de Luce and the Crowne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>F.H. = Francis Herring.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: De veri et falsi medici cognitione.</note>
                  <note>"A discouery of certaine strategems, whereby our English emperickes haue bene obserued strongly to oppugne, and oft times to expugne their poore patients purses", by Francis Herring, has caption title on D4r.</note>
                  <note>Printe's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medical ethics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quacks and quackery --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21413:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANATOMYES of the True Phyſition, and Counterfeit <hi>Mounte-banke:</hi> wherein both of them, are graphically deſcribed, and ſet out in their Right, and Orient Colours.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed in Latin by <hi>Iohn Oberndorff,</hi> a Learned German: and Tranſlated into Engliſh by <hi>F.H.</hi> Fellow of the Coll. of Phyſitions in <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Herevnto is annexed: A ſhort Diſcourſe, or, Diſcouery of certaine Stratagems, whereby our London-Empericks, haue bene ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued ſtrongly to oppugne, and oft times to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne their Poore Patients Purſes.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed for Arthur Iohnſon, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Powles Church-yard, at the Signe of the Flower de Luce and the Crowne. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21413:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21413:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Syr <hi>Iohn Popham,</hi> Knight, Lord chiefe Iuſtice of England, and One of her <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties most Honourable priuie Councell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Alen</hi> one of the moſt famous Well-ſprings of Phyloſophie and Phyſicke (Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable) compareth,<note place="margin">Lib. de praecog. ad Poſt hun qui rep. Tomo quarte.</note> vnlettered Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rickes and Quack-ſaluers, vnto Theeues, and Robbers; making this only difference betwixt them, <hi>Quod hi in Montibus &amp; Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis, Illi, in confortiſs. Vrbibus inſidientur.</hi> That is, they take a Purſe by the high-way, in Woods or Forreſts, but theſe do it in the moſt frequented and Populous Cities. This graue, Iuditiall, and Peremptory verdit and ſentence, of that great Phyloſopher, and renowmed Phyſition, dooth more cloſely attach, and ſtrongly arreſt our ignorant Intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and bolde Periclitators in the Practiſe of Phyſicke, then all the world is aware of. This (I hope) ſhall euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeare vnto your L. by the two Treatiſes enſuing, the one of them, being written in Latin by a Learned German, and by me put into an Engliſh Coate, for the good of my Country-men: and the other, a ſhort Obſeruation of mine owne.</p>
            <p>It is a <hi>Maxime</hi> among Diuines, that <hi>Simulata Sanctitaes, eſt duplex Iniquitas.</hi> In like ſort it may be ſaid, that fained know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:21413:3"/>
is double Ignorance, both becauſe it is Ignorance, and becauſe it lyeth, and counterfeiteth Skill and Science. For if it be a point and part of good wiſedome, for a man to ſee and acknowledge his owne weakneſſe and inſufficiency, and therevpon, to keepe within Compaſſe, and meddle not (with the Shoe-maker) <hi>Vltra Crepidam:</hi> It muſt needs be an increaſe of Folly, Vanitie, and Arrogance, for any, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Skill and knowledge in thoſe Things wherein they are altogether vnacquainted, and to profeſſe thoſe Arts, which they neuer learned. But our Emperickes and Impoſtors, as they are too ignorant either to Teach or Practiſe Phyſicke (which they neuer ſaluted from the threskhold) and too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent, and arrogant to learne of the Maiſters of that Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or to be reduced into Order; ſo are they moſt dangerous and pernitious vnto the Weale-publike. Among wild Beaſts (ſaith one) Enuy is moſt Sauadge &amp; exitiall, and among ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Beaſts Flattery. The reaſon is, becauſe the Sycophant is leaſt of all feared, and moſt difficultly diſcerned and diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Theſe Crocodils, diſguiſed with the vizard of fained Knowledge, and masking vnder the ſpecious Titles of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and Doctors, not attained in Schooles, but impoſed by the Common people, do with their Abſolonicall Saluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſteale away the affections of the inconſtant Multitude, from the Learned Profeſſors of that Facultie, and with their Loablike Imbracings, ſtabbe to the hart their poore and ſilly Patients, ere they be aware, or once ſuſpect ſuch vncouth Trechery. The more worthy &amp; excellent the Obiect of any Art is, the greater, and more daungerous is the Error of the <hi>Artist,</hi> if he faile in his Office. If a Taylor marre a Garment, or the Potter breake the Veſſell he ſhould make, the matter is not great. But as he ſaid in the Comicall Poet, <hi>Graue eſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riculu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Filio:</hi> So great is the Hazard, and greater is the Fault committed in the Bodie of Man, the Domicil and Palace of the immortall Soule, and (as <hi>Zoroaſter</hi> calleth it) <hi>audacis Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae
<pb facs="tcp:21413:3"/>
ſtupendum Miraculum.</hi> I omit as ſmall matter, their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vpon the Spoile, and deceiuing the People of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſubſtance (which yet the good Magiſtrate doth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly reſpect) but their hainous offences againſt the pretious Health and Life of Men, (whereof London hath many wofull Experiments in a yeare) are altogether intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and in no wiſe to be ſilenced or pretermitted. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe it is ſtraunge to behold, and conſider, how theſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumforanian Impoſtors are dignified by the People, flocked and reſorted vnto in whole Troupes, ſought out far &amp; neare, and equalized with, nay (which is the greateſt Indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of all other) preferred &amp; extolled before the moſt Graue, Learned, and beſt Experienced in that Profeſſion. If a man haue a ſcruple in Conſcience, hee will not repaire vnto an Hedge-prieſt (as they are called) or bare Reader, hauing no more Diuinitie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Child of ten yeares old, for reſolution, but to ſome Learned, godly and Iuditiall Diuine. If a Suit in Lawe, he will not reſort to a Husbandman or Artificer, for Counſell and Direction, but to a Skilfull, well ſtudyed, and approoued Lawyer: And yet (ſuch is the extreme folly and madneſſe of many Men), that in caſe of Health and Life, (Things moſt pretious) they think euery Tinker, Bankerupt, or wandering Fugitiue, who hath ouer runne his Creditors, forſaken his Trade, and ſeeketh to liue (like a Droan without any Calling) a ſufficient and compleat Phyſition, to aduiſe, counſell, and direct them. It will be ſaid, that theſe Good-fellowes haue bene obſerued to performe ſome Cures, and to haue good ſucceſſe in their Actions. It hath bene likewiſe knowne, that a common Mariner, the Maiſter and Gouernor of the ſhip dying, or miſcarying by ſome Accident, hath ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought the Barke to ſhore, and arriued at the wiſhed Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and yet no man (if hee may chuſe) will willingly ſayle with ſuch a Pylot. A Company of vntrained and rawe Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, which neuer ſaw Field or Warre before, haue vanqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,
<pb facs="tcp:21413:4"/>
and put to flight a Band of Veterans, invred for many yeares, and well exerciſed in martiall Affaires. And yet no Commaunder will prefer the punee, and freſh-water Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, before the auncient, tryed, and well-diſciplined Warri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. <hi>Vna hirundo non facit Ver,</hi> Though that bee admitted (which notwithſtanding if the Inſtances be well ſcanned) will be a difficult matter to proue) yet I hold firmly (with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable <hi>Galen</hi>) my former <hi>Poſition,</hi> that they are bad and dangerous Members of the State, and in no ſort ſufferable in any well-ordered Common-wealth. I do therefore preſume to offer theſe my ſlender trauailes vnto your L. who as you are a zealous Louer of your Country, a for-ward Profeſſor of the Goſpell, an incorrupt, and vpright Iuſticer, a Friend to Vertue and Men of Deſert, a profeſſed Aduerſary to all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors: So I nothing doubt, but you wil take vpon you the Patronage, of the Learned and honeſt Phyſition, againſt the Ignorant and Couzening <hi>Mounte-banke.</hi> Among your other manifolde, and Honourable ſeruices, performed to your Prince, and Country, (wherby you haue commended your Name and Memorie to all Poſteritie), it is not the laſt nor leaſt, that by your watchfull Prouidence, and healthfull Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice you haue cut off great numbers of Graſſators, and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and in a maner, clenſed, ſcoured and rid the Realme, of thoſe Monſters, and ſauadge rauenous Beaſts in the ſhape of Men. And I am perſwaded, that your Ho. Endeuours in fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering and contenancing the catching and ſuppreſſing of theſe tame Beaſts, or rather wily Foxes and Panthers, who with their ſubtile fleights, ſugred words, and ſweet ſents, do allure, entrap, and circumuent the Simple, and pray vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both their Goods and Bodies at their pleaſure, will be no leſſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, profitable to your Country, gratefull and commendable vnto all ſucceeding Ages, then the former. But I need not ſpend words in perſwading your L. who haue alreadie declared, your Honourable Inclination and
<pb facs="tcp:21413:4"/>
forwardneſſe vnto that Buſineſſe. Therefore fearing to be te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, I deſire only the continuance of your Honourable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour vnto the Societie whereof I am, in their iuſt and honeſt Cauſes, &amp; Affaires, and wiſh vnto your L. from my moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affections, increaſe of Honor, Length of Dayes, proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous ſucceſſe in all your Honourable Enterpriſes for Gods Church, and your Countries Good, Health of Body, Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie of mind, compleat Faelicitie in this world, and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Happineſſe in that, which is to come.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ho. most humble, and addicted Clyent. <hi>F. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:21413:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21413:5"/>
            <head>IN ERVDITISSIMAM DISSERTATIONEM DE VE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro &amp; falſo Medico, Clariſſimi &amp; dexter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimi <hi>Medici Domini D. Ioannis O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borndorfii.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>Epigramma.</head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>VI Squis es infestis, qui conflictabere morbis,</l>
            <l>Fac ratio Luctae conſtet vt ista tuae.</l>
            <l>Fluctuat, incerto Natura relicta a duello:</l>
            <l>Auxiliatricemqúe indiga poſcit opem.</l>
            <l>Si rectum quaeras Medicum: geminaueris ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtem</l>
            <l>Morbo, &amp; victrici congrediêre manu.</l>
            <l>Sin faiſum: gemino Natura occumbet ah hoste:</l>
            <l>Nam<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> nec <hi>Alcides</hi> ſustinet ipſe duos.</l>
            <l>Hinc malè ſi proprijs ſe credit viribus aeger,</l>
            <l>Peius ad inſulſum confugiet Medicum.</l>
            <l>Ergò ne pecces, hoc erudiêre libello,</l>
            <l>Hoſtem vt praevertas, Theſea quaere tuum.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Caſpar Stemper D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:21413:6"/>
            <head>IN THEOREMATA DE VERO MEDICO, NOBILIS ET CLARISSIMI VIRI, Domini Ioannis Oberndorfferi, Phyſici <hi>&amp; Medici celeberrimi.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Seudo prophetae Orbem Cacocauſſidici<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> replêrunt,</l>
            <l>Quid Medicos mirum gliſcere degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res?</l>
            <l>De puduiſſe quibus decus eſt, qui pectora fraude</l>
            <l>Plena, manus letho, labra Thraſonis, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent.</l>
            <l>Multum vaſa ſonant inflata, &amp; inania ſemper,</l>
            <l>Strenuus ore magis, quò magis arte rudis.</l>
            <l>Nequior vt<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> quis eſt linguâ, ſic jura fidem<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>
            </l>
            <l>Promptior aſtutis diſſecat inſidijs.</l>
            <l>O nimium tortos prauâ vortigine ſenſus,</l>
            <l>Orbem, at non dabitur ludificare IOVAM.</l>
            <l>Quando venit ſcelerum grauis &amp; iuſtiſſimus vltor,</l>
            <l>Fraus, fraudiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> faber quilibet, igne perit.</l>
            <l>Interea felix, qui quit dignoſcere VERVM.</l>
            <l>A FALSO: oris IOVAE, inſtar is eſt DOMINI.</l>
            <l>A VLLI educis Medicâ PRECIOSIVS Arte,</l>
            <l>IANE, &amp; O BERNDORFFI hinc nobile nomen ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes,</l>
            <l>Nobile nomen habes, genus &amp; doctrina SVPREMVM</l>
            <l>Tefaciunt Medico nempè cluére Choro,</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. Chriſtophorus Dana vêrus Ratiſp. P. L. l. m. accinebat.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:21413:6"/>
            <head>AD NOBILEM ET CLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RISSMVM VIRVM, IOANNEM Oberndorfferum, Medicae diſciplinae Doctorem: in ſuam Veri Falſi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Medici Schemam.</head>
            <l>OMnia nunc paſsim toto vertuntur in ORBE;</l>
            <l>Flebile ad exitium cuncta minanter eunt.</l>
            <l>ARTES diſpereunt meliori ſemine natae,</l>
            <l>At<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſuas miſerae ſemper habent ſtrigilies.</l>
            <l>Prostrant Artifices Docti non aſſe vel vno:</l>
            <l>Vulgus apud fatuum docta cohors perijt.</l>
            <l>Et quid non tentant exoſa <hi>Catharmata:</hi> LEGIS</l>
            <l>Diuinae ſatagunt commaculare Libros.</l>
            <l>Enthea conſpurcant mysteria; fronte petulcâ</l>
            <l>Audent in Magnum verba tonare Deum.</l>
            <l>Ecce Fori Coruos ex illâ parte; furenter</l>
            <l>In SACRA IVSTITIAE quàm ſine menterunnt?</l>
            <l>Inceſſu grandi grallant, tetramqúe ſuperbè</l>
            <l>Depreſſant, oculis, vultu, animoqúe Truces.</l>
            <l>Scilicet &amp; ſunt HI quos Tu cane peius &amp; angue</l>
            <l>Vitabis, benè qui diſcupis eſſe Tibi.</l>
            <l>In MEDICA felix quis non hodiè Arte triumphat:</l>
            <l>Quin quo<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Naturá proſiliunt Medici.</l>
            <l>Spermologi, errones, nactae, monachi fugitiui</l>
            <l>Divendunt Medicas indubitanter opes.</l>
            <l>Fures, Carnifices, &amp; quae de faece popelli</l>
            <l>Res propè decoxit perdita turba ſuas:</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21413:7"/>Omnes hi Medici venerando nomine gaudent:</l>
            <l>Et quod turpè magis, turpè, ſenilis Anus.</l>
            <l>O MEDICINA, DEI quae prodita ab ore pateſcis,</l>
            <l>Tam foedis pedibus (proh) temerata iaces.</l>
            <l>Exulat, HIPPOCRATIS Diuina ſcientia, nemo</l>
            <l>Ingenium ſequitur, docte GALENE, tuum.</l>
            <l>Quilibet ex proprio fabricat medicamina ſenſu:</l>
            <l>Pro placito fingit gramina nata ſibi.</l>
            <l>Morborum quaeris ſi cauſas: abdita ſunt haec,</l>
            <l>Reſponſant, ſibi quae vendicat ipſe DEVS:</l>
            <l>Quas non inquiri fas est ſine crimine magno.</l>
            <l>Sic<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> rudem ludunt turpiter Arte gregem.</l>
            <l>At Tu, qui triplici munitus pectora ferro,</l>
            <l>Tam malè tornatos non bibis anre ſonos:</l>
            <l>Fluctuat in dubiâ tamen heîc ſententia mente,</l>
            <l>Veri quae MEDICI certa figura ſiet:</l>
            <l>Hunc cape, quem donat nativâ ex arte Libellum</l>
            <l>OBERNDORFFERI ſedula cura Tibi.</l>
            <l>Pellege, ſed praeſens animo, Livore ſubacto:</l>
            <l>Livor enim planâ neſcit inire viâ.)</l>
            <l>Is TE ductabit per amoena vireta: docebit,</l>
            <l>Perdiſcas MEDICVM queî benè noſſe VIRVM.</l>
            <l>Monſtrat inaniloquos, impoſtoreſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> nefandos:</l>
            <l>Qui populoqúe ſolent impoſuiſſe rudi.</l>
            <l>Hos ſi cognoſcis: Tu grata mente memento</l>
            <l>AVCTORI grates nolle negare ſuas.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Martinus Oberndorfferus, Cantiaebius Palatinus, Iurisprud. ſtud.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21413:7"/>
            <head>THE ANATOMYES of the True Phyſition, and counterfeit <hi>Mounte-banke:</hi> wherin both of them, are graphically deſcribed, and ſet <hi>ſet out in their right and Orient colours.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="antithesis">
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>Antitheſis. <hi>1.</hi> Part. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoeuer purpoſeth to attaine the right noble,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and diuine Science of Phyſicke, and to become a true, and worthie <hi>Aſclepiadean:</hi> before all things, it is requiſite, that he be wholly carryed, and as it were rauiſhed, with a naturall &amp; heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call inſtinct and inclination vnto that Studie.</p>
                  <p>For it is not poſſible for any man, vnleſſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> he be caſt in Natures mould, and by her faſhioned for that Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to performe any thing therein, worth a Ruſh.</p>
                  <p>But he that is therevnto framed, and diſpoſed by Natures indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> doth not only in a ſhort time, make happie proceedings in the knowledge of that high and learned Facultie, but doth likewiſe, witti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and diſcreetly, apply himſelfe vnto the preceptions, acting, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming in the view of the world, ſome famous Worke, of great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, and admiration.</p>
                  <p>Eſpecially if he be of an ingenuous, and Schollerlike Diſpoſition,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> willing and readie to receiue Inſtruction and Profit, by whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
                  <p>For this is the very ſtore-houſe of Erudition, the moſt neceſſary <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and precious Iewell of life, the Treaſure, and Light of Science.</p>
                  <p>Who before hee ſet vpon, ſo long and laborious a Studie, beſide <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> honeſtie of life, and ciuilitie of manners, is poliſhed and adorned with <hi>Pallas</hi> golden chaine: <hi>I</hi> mean throughly furniſhed, with thoſe Arts and Tongues, which are moſt requiſite and neceſſary in a Phyſition.</p>
                  <p>For theſe are the well-ſprings and Fountaines of all humanitie,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21413:8"/>
wherewith if our Phyſition be not throughly watered, he can neuer bring forth any good or wholeſome Fruite. For as theſe liberall and generall Arts leade vs (as it were by the hand) to the ſweete and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſtreames of Naturall Philoſophie: ſo Philoſophie bringeth vs (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome good acquaintance with her) to the ſpacious, goodly, &amp; beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Field of Phyſicke.</p>
                  <p>It is needfull likewiſe, that hee bring with him an eager ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, and inſatiable Deſire, to penetrate, and diue into the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of that profound Science: wherein there are ſo many hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſecrets, farre remoued from the Eyes &amp; Sence of the Vulgar ſort.</p>
                  <p>Wherevpon, that hee may the more eaſily and happily attaine the knowledge of theſe things, he placeth himſelfe in ſome famous V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſitie, repleniſhed by the benigne aſpect of Heauen, &amp; clemency of the Aire &amp; Soyle, with refined and braue Wits: where (as in a Mart of Phiſicke) he doth not only ſtore himſelfe with varietie of medicinal furniture of all kindes; but doth likewiſe often enter into the liſts with his Corriuals, &amp; exerciſeth himſelf in diſcuſſing the difficult Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies, of that learned Facultie: chuſing for his Maiſters &amp; Standerd-bearers, ſuch as are of greateſt learning, and moſt renowmed &amp; happy Practiſe, and ſuch as do teach the Art painfully and faithfully, that by theſe meanes he may more ioyfully and ſpeedily aſpire vnto the top of his Deſires.</p>
                  <p>Neither is he wanting to himſelfe, but duly waying that Occaſion is ſwift, ſlippery, and bald behind, he catcheth her by her fore-lockes: with daily and ſingular diligence he ſtriketh the Iron, while it is hote, and taketh the Time whileſt Time ſerueth.</p>
                  <p>By this meanes, he layeth a ſound and ſure foundation of his Art, readily apprehending, firmly retaining the precepts thereof, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently applying them to the vſe of his Patients.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer, he ſeriouſly bethinketh himſelfe, that this diuine, and moſt learned Study, requireth not a laizie, drowzie, and ſlothful-ſnor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Therfites:</hi> but a painfull, vigilant, and induſtrious <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> hauing a chearfull and vndanted Mind, againſt all dangers, and troubles what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</p>
                  <p>Herevpon he daily &amp; painfully exerciſeth himſelfe in reading the learned volumes of thoſe auncient Worthies, who haue faithfully, and fruitfully deliuered this Art vnto Poſterity, the only Solace of humane Life: he diligently frequenteth the publike Lectures of Anatomy: and afterward himſelfe doth make open Diſſection. To conclude, he ſpareth no paine, but climbeth the high &amp; ſteep Mountains, rangeth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21413:8"/>
thorow the low vallies, pierceth the woods and thickets, entereth the Caues and hollow Dens of the earth, ſearcheth thorowly the ſpatious and wild fields, the banks of ſweet &amp; running Riuers, to attain the true knowledge and nature of multiforme Simples.</p>
                  <p>And that bee may comprehend and vnderſtand the nature, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, and vertues of all theſe, he refuſeth no trauaile, nor forbeareth any coſt, referring and applying them all, to the commoditie, benefit, and health of Men.</p>
                  <p>In the meane while (like a <hi>Diogenes</hi> or <hi>Timon,</hi> who deſires to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone and ſingular) he doth not refuſe to ioyne with learned Phiſitions, when they viſit their Patients, and conferre together about the cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Diſeaſes: but doth heedfully obſerue thoſe learned Colloquies, and Conſultations, and carefully commit them to memory: putting likewiſe his owne hand by little and litle vnto the worke, and in Caſes of difficultie and danger, is nothing aſhamed to follow the Aduiſe and Direction of skilfull and well-pratiſed Phyſitions.</p>
                  <p>But to atchiue all theſe things happily, and ſucceſſiuely, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Time and Opportunitie are neceſſarily required.</p>
                  <p>For the learned, ample and diuine Art of Phyſicke, which requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a whole man, is not learned in the ſpace of one or two yeares: but for the largeneſſe, excellency, worthineſſe, and profunditie thereof, the whole Life of man is hardly ſufficient.</p>
                  <p>If we expect that this heauenly Science implanted in the mind, and purchaſed by ſo many ſweats, and more then <hi>Herculean</hi> Labors, ſhould yeeld a plentifull harueſt to the good, &amp; welfare of Mankind.</p>
                  <p>Thus you haue briefly (as it were) the birth, education, &amp; inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a true <hi>Aeſculapian:</hi> to whom if you oppoſe your Changeling and masking <hi>Mounte banke,</hi> you ſhall finde them to agree like Harpe and Harrow. 2.</p>
                  <p>For it is clearer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sun, that the whole Rable of theſe Quack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaluers, are of a baſe wit, &amp; peruerſe Nature, hauing no more naturall Inclination, or Diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto this ſtudy, then the Aſſe to the harpe.</p>
                  <p>For all theſe Bragadocian <hi>Theſſali,</hi> which boaſt of their skill in this Profeſſion, couering their Aſſes eares, with the honeſt tytles of Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors &amp; Phyſitions, as with a comely Mantel, and practiſing Phyſick to the vnauoydable and lamentable hurt and danger, of their poore and miſerakle Patients, if you conſider them aright, for the moſt part are the abiect &amp; ſordidous ſcumme, and refuſe of the people, who hauing runne away from their Trades and Occupations, learne in a corner, to get their liuings, by killing of Men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21413:9"/>And if we plucke off the vizards wherein theſe diſguiſed Maskers do march, &amp; bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Light which (like Owles) they cannot abide, they will appeare to be runnagate Iewes, the cut-throats and robbers of Chriſtians, ſlowbellyed Monkes, who haue made eſcape from their Cloyſters, Simoniacall and periured ſhauelings, buſie Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> lackla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, Thrafonical, and vnlettered Chymiſts, ſhifting &amp; outcaſt Petti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foggers, light-headed, and triuiall Druggers, and Apothecaries, Sun-ſhunning night birds, and Corner-creepers, dull-pated, and baſe Mechanickes, Stage-players, Iuglers, Pedlers, prittle-pratling Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, filthie Graſiers, curious Bath-keepers, common ſhifters, &amp; cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Caueliers, bragging Soldiers, Bankerupt marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, lazy Clowns, one-eyed or lamed Fencers, toothleſſe and tatling old wiues, chatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Char-women, and Nurſ-keepers, long tongued Midwiues, ſcape-Tibornes, Dog-leethes, and ſuch like baggage, and earth dung.</p>
                  <p>In the next Ranke, to ſecond this goodly and ſweet Troupe, follow Poyſoners, Inchanters, Soothſayers, Wizards, Fortune-tellers, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitians, Witches, Hags, with a rablement moe, of that damnable Crew, the very filth and droſſe of the world.</p>
                  <p>Now, if you take a good view of theſe ſweet Companions, you ſhall finde them, not only meere Dolts, Idiots, and Buzzards: but likewiſe Conremners and Haters of all good learning.</p>
                  <p>For the greateſt part of them diſdaine booke-learning, being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnacquainted with liberal Arts, and neuer came where Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning grew.</p>
                  <p>For euery one of them, though in his own opinion an other <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> yet either hath no bookes at all, or if hee haue a great Library, to make the world beleeue hee is a great Clarke, yet hee layeth them by the walles to feed the Moathes, but neuer peruſeth them: nay many times cannot, ſo groſſe is his Ignorance.</p>
                  <p>For Bookes (witneſſe <hi>Galen,</hi> the incomparable Maiſter of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke) are Monuments, and Regiſters, of thoſe who are before lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and no perfect Inſtruction for Rudsbies, and Idiots.</p>
                  <p>Neither doth the poſſeſſion of a great Library, and multitude of Bookes, make a man learned: no more then <hi>Aiax</hi> armor would make <hi>Thirſites</hi> a ſtout Souldier: But the painful and diligent reading them, and applying them to vſe: as the skilfull vſe of weapons, not the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of them ſhoweth and proueth a good Warriour.</p>
                  <p>But theſe (for the moſt part) ruſh into <hi>Apolloes</hi> Temple, with vnwaſhen handes, and vnlettered heades: and as they are as blinde as Beetles, ſo they haue not ſo much as a deſire to ſee into the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21413:9"/>
of that abſtruſe Facultie: they either vſe no Teachers at all, or elſe make choiſe of ſome Theſſalicall Empericks as learned as themſelues, or ſome ſmoaky Chymiſt, or black <hi>Vulcane,</hi> able to teach them nothing but that which muſt afterward be vntaught: yet notwithſtanding they ſwell like the Terentian Thraſo, with a vaine and phoppiſh conceit of skill and knowledge, as though they were the onely profound Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and learned Phiſitions of the world. To conclude, they are ſuch as cannot abide to take any paines or trauell in ſtudie: they reiect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable <hi>Galens</hi> learned Commentaries, as tedious and friuolous Diſcourſes, hauing found thorow <hi>Paracelſus</hi> Vulcanian ſhop, a more compendious and ſhort way to the Wood: ſpending <hi>Tyme,</hi> the moſt noble and precious creature of God, either with dooing nothing, or vainly and fooliſhly, about toyes, as in finding the Fooloſophers ſtone, making Potable gold, or in doing that which is euill and pernitious, as in making ſome pleaſant &amp; refined poyſons, vnder the names of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bith minerall, or Butyrum Arſenici, to keepe <hi>Charon</hi> from wanting worke; or elſe with a troubled and ſhittle head, toſſed too and fro like a feather, and turning as oft as the weather-cock, they neuer bring any thing to good effect, or perfection.</p>
                  <p>Others are ſo notoriouſly ſottiſh, that being ouer head and eares in the myrie puddle of groſſe Ignorance, yet they will by no meanes ſee or acknowledge it: ſo that they know not ſo much, as that they know nothing.</p>
                  <p>For to giue an inſtance in the moſt abſolute, exquiſite, and diuine frame of mans Body, if they can ſhewe a rude Deſcription thereof, hanging in their chamber, and nick-name two or three parts (ſo as it would make a horſe to breake his halter to heare them) they think themſelues iolly fellowes, and are eſteemed great Anatomiſts in the eyes of the Vulgars.</p>
                  <p>Now in the knowledge of Plants they are old excellent, and will roundly ſhewe you Spynach in ſtead of Sorrell, a Nettle for Betony, and Colchicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for Saffron, &amp; that very demurely without any bluſhing.</p>
                  <p>Others (as wiſe as theſe) affirme very confidently, if not impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the knowledge of Plants and other ſimples, appartaineth not vnto them, but to the Apothecaries.</p>
                  <p>But it ſeemeth to me very ridiculous, if not altogether diſhono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and ignominious, that he who taketh vpon him to be an other <hi>Apollo</hi> and great Doctor, ſhould not know the Inſtruments of his owne Art.</p>
                  <p>Now they are not ſo ignorant &amp; doltiſh, but they are as enuious,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21413:10"/>
impudent, and wainſcot-faced. And ſince there is no puniſhment allotted vnto Ignorance in the weale publike, ſauing the blot and brand of Infamy, that is ſo familiar and accuſtomed vnto them from the cradle, that it toucheth them no more then a flea-byting. And Impudencie is ſo rooted in the bones, and bred in the fleſh, that they not onely in ſecret laſh and whip with their venemous and ſerpentine Tongues, all honeſt and learned Phiſitions, but at their pleaſures do tyranniſe and excarnificat mens bodies, and through their bayard like boldneſſe, and licentious impunitie, make hauocke of their ſilly Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, making experiments, and trying their Tartareall concluſions, by more then Tragicall Deaths.</p>
                  <p>For there is no crime ſo haynous or odious, which lewd and loſt Companions do not perpetrate, vnleſſe they be bridled and reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by feare of puniſhment: but if the Magiſtrate looke thorow the fingers, and winke at their naughtineſſe, or elſe maintaine and patroci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate them therin, then they carrie all away ſmoothly, and ſleep ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on both ſides.</p>
                  <p>But theſe men ſhould doo farre better, neuer to vndertake thoſe things wherein they haue no skill, then to profeſſe thoſe Arts which they neuer learned.</p>
                  <p>Now it is the honeſteſt and ſafeſt courſe for good and learned Phiſitions, (ſince they haue no power in their hand to redreſſe theſe Enormities, and that there is ſmall hope of a better world) to haue no ſocietie with theſe Barbarians, enemies to all Antiquitie, Humanitie, and good learning, leaſt they heare the old ſaying, <hi>Like will to like.</hi> As was ſaid of the Diuell dauncing with the Collier.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="antithesis">
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>Antitheſis. <hi>2.</hi> 1. Part.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F we from hence proceed to the Courſe of life, and practiſe of a right <hi>Aeſculapian,</hi> wee ſhall ſee him differ as much as white and blacke, from the croa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and hedge creeping Quack-ſaluer.</p>
                  <p>His maine and principall drift and endeuour, by meanes of his education in thoſe ſtudies, which wholly rauiſh the mind with the loue of Vertue, is, that as a faithfull friend, and well-willer of Nature he may religiouſly, vnſpottedly, &amp; charily preſerue the precious healt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21413:10"/>
and life of man, and conſerue the Eſtimation &amp; Dignitie of that moſt honorable and worthy Profeſſion.</p>
                  <p>For he thorowly wayeth and conſidereth the excellencie of his Arts ſubiect, Man, that noble, admirable, and incomparable worke of <hi>Iehouah,</hi> the Temple of the holy Ghoſt, the moſt eminent and cleare Myrrour, &amp; Spectacle among all creatures, of the diuine wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Iuſtice, Goodneſſe, I ſay Man framed after the ſimilitude of the Eternall.</p>
                  <p>Which noble and worthy Creature, committeth his deareſt Selfe and Life into the hands and truſt of our Phiſition.</p>
                  <p>Concerning whom, together with all his Operations, &amp; Practiſes in his Facultie, he is to giue account vnto Nature and the Author ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: the Eternall as a carefull Inſpector, &amp; ſincere Iudge of them, in the day of that great &amp; general Aſſiſe, &amp; euerlaſting Sabaoth of the world.</p>
                  <p>When hee ſeriouſly and diligently pondereth theſe things, hee muſt needs remember his owne Condition, and that it concernes him to looke well to the vpſhot and Concluſion.</p>
                  <p>Herevpon he attempteth nothing, he appointeth and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth nothing, but with ſound Aduice, Councel, &amp; Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſearching out with great care, induſtrie, and diligence, the nature and force of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Maladies (weighing all things in the ballances of Reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) with great and ſingular Dexteritie repelling them, and with admirable wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, foretelling and preſaging future Calamities.</p>
                  <p>He accounteth nothing more deare vnto him, then the Health of his Patients, wherevnto he is wholly deuoted, refuſing no labour or danger, be it neuer ſo imminent, to attaine that end. Nay he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumeth himſelfe with griefe and care for other mens Calamities, reckoning their woes, his owne miſeries: and all to this end, that hee may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the office of a true Phiſition, and deliuer his Patients from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auoydable Perils, and reſcue men as it were out of the iawes of Death.</p>
                  <p>For Phiſicke being the Art of helping and healing, not of killing and excarnificating, (as <hi>Scribonius</hi> ſaith well) the Profeſſor thereof, our Phiſition, dooth not value men by their Fortunes, and Places in the world, but reacheth out his helping and healthfull Hand vnto all that deſire his aſſiſtance, and maketh ſure neuer to hurt any, but helpe as many as poſſibly he can.</p>
                  <p>Herevpon, as beſeemeth a good and vertuous Man, hee carrieth not two faces vnder one Hood, but his Heart and Tongue, his words and actions agree and goe hand in hand together.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21413:11"/>For he endeuoreth by all meanes to ſhew himſelfe prudent, baſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, truſtie, graue, modeſt, conſtant, couragious, courteous, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fable.</p>
                  <p>For all theſe faire Vertues do vſually attend them, who haue bene rightly conuerſant, and trained vp in <hi>Apolloes</hi> Schoole.</p>
                  <p>Among other Vertues hee greatly embraceth Taciturnitie, and Secreſie. For there are many Miſteries of the Art, many Diſeaſes of Patients, which to blab abroad, were neither ſeemly nor expedient. Many things are ſaid and done by theſe like parties, many Accidents fall out in their houſes, which are to be concealed as Secrets, and not to be carried out of doores, and cryed at the Croſſe.</p>
                  <p>For it is a Signe and argument of a Gentleman-like Diſpoſition, and amiable Diſcretion, to keepe cloſe things to be ſecreted, leaſt all our Wit ſeeme to lie in our tongues end, and not to be lodged in the Head or Heart.</p>
                  <p>And as he is ſecret and diſcreet, ſo is he likewiſe Sober and Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, that he may be fit &amp; readie to viſite his Patients, at any houre of the day or night: being as good an afternoones-man, as a mornings-man.</p>
                  <p>For as <hi>Galen</hi> witneſſeth, a good Phiſition ought to bee as ſtudious of Sobrietie, as of Veritie.</p>
                  <p>So in his attire there is no ſuperfluous Curioſitie, Courtlike Pomp, far-fetched &amp; fooliſh Finicallitie: no nor Diogenicall naſtineſſe, and Lazerlike ſlouenie: but therein he laboureth to be decent, comely, and frugall.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer he is contented with a mediocritie, and ioyeth in a meane Eſtate, not greedily gaping and breathing after Riches, being ſufficient to himſelfe, and knowing that they of their owne accord, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low an induſtrious and laborious Hand, vnleſſe a Mans lot fall among ſuch as are altogether Clownes and Sowters.</p>
                  <p>And that he may auoyd all ſiniſter Cogitations, and Suſpitions of euill, and vnhoneſt dealing, he cautelouſly ſhunneth and ſhutteth out all churliſh, malignant, new-found, &amp; ſuſpected medicines, admitting thoſe onely in his Practiſe, which are eaſie, ſafe, benigne, vndoubted, ſecure, and approued by long Vſe, and certaine Experience of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Worthies, and great Maiſters in Phiſicke.</p>
                  <p>And in all theſe things hee carrieth himſelfe diſcreetly, ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, &amp; without Cunning and Deceit: not refuſing to ſubmit his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts and Formes (if need require) to the Cenſure and Iudgement of learned Phiſitions, willingly yealding to conferre with them, and (to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21413:11"/>
vſe great <hi>Hippocrates</hi> words) embracing willingly any learned Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie, leaſt by any meanes he ſhould ſeeme to play the Coward or Flin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</p>
                  <p>For Truth being of that Nature, that ſhe neuer hideth her Face, or feareth to behold the Light, ſo the true Philoſopher or Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (for thoſe two in our Age make one) is ſociable, &amp; readie to communicate, hearing other mens Opinions and Iudgement with great delight, only to this intent, that by this friendly Conference, and diligent Inueſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he may be confirmed and incouraged in his good Courſe, and the Patient receiue more aſſured, and certaine Benefites.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>2.</hi> Antitheſis. 2. Part.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow if you compare with him, our ſuborned and masking <hi>Mounte-barke,</hi> whoſe wits are as dull as a doore nale, they will be found as farre different and diſtant, as <hi>Michaels</hi> Mount, and <hi>Cheuen</hi> Hills.</p>
                  <p>For where ſhal you finde any one in this Crew, who hath any ſpark of Religion, or drop of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? where one that hath any right ſence of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, or common Humanitie? But to ſpeake plaine, (though it be horrible, ſo much as to thinke) the greateſt part of this Packe, are no better then ranke and arrant Atheiſts.</p>
                  <p>And to ſpeake within compaſſe, you ſhall ſooner finde a blacke Swan, then an honeſt man in this Bunch: but if you prye narrowly into them, you ſhall diſcerne notorious Impoſtores, olde bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Foxes, and Cozeners; not Friends and Fauorites, but ſworne Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Nature, and Man-kinde: laughing in their ſleeues at their Budget full of wyles which they carrie in their boſome, moſt baſely and wickedly, proſtituting both Themſelues, and the Art.</p>
                  <p>For this loſt Companion, hauing a Foxes Head, and an whoriſh and wainſcotted Face, conſidering that nothing is ſet by in this Age, but that which is profitable, that wealth is more eſteemed then Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and that Riches make the Gentleman, and that Money maketh Vertue ſtand behinde the doore, he ſetteth this downe as a Maxime, and Concluſion, that wealth muſt be had, though with the Iniurie and wracke of Pietie, Equitie, Humanitie, and common Honeſtie, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21413:12"/>
priſing Man, that immortall, and excellent Creature, the grand Myracle of the Eternall, at naught, hee carrieth himſelfe Impiouſly, Deſperately, and Craftily, in all his Courſes, caſting as it were the Dice vpon his Patients.</p>
                  <p>Herevpon he pronounceth all Things darkly and doubtfully, as if <hi>Apollo</hi> ſhould gaue Oracles from his Threefooted ſtoole. And if he happen at any Time on a Truth, you muſt pardon him, it was more then he was aware of. Now, all is Cocke ſure, hee will pawne his Life and Credit (not both worth a Ruſh) all ſhall bee well. By and by, with a Stoicall Countenance, he threatneth Daunger and Death: breathing at once both cold and hotte, and all to this End: that which way ſo euer the World waggeth, hee may bee thought by his great Wiſedome, and deepe reach in Diuining, to haue foreſeene and preſaged the Euent: which he foreknew as much as a Woodcocke.</p>
                  <p>So that beeing himſelfe more variable then the Polyp, hee is in twentie ſeuerall Mindes in an houre, turning and winding, too and fro, like a Tragedians Buskin, and vttering quite Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes.</p>
                  <p>Thus doth this baſe and lewd Couzener mocke God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe Man, for whoſe cauſe the Eternall created the goodly and beautifull Frame of the World: and in whoſe Bodie, whatſoeuer is more largely in that Spatious, and Gorgious Pallace, and Theater delineated, is more briefly comptiſed, and as it were Epitomiſed, and repreſented a ſhort Summe or Viewe. Againſt this Noble Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the ſmall Counterfeit of the Great GOD, hee dooth oft times rage more ſauagely, then any wilde Beare, or Tygar, refuſing all good, ſafe, and wholſome Medicines, and purpoſely making Choiſe of them which were inuented by Sathan or his Imps, for the ruine, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Mankind.</p>
                  <p>Now his Manners and Conditions (the liuely Characters of the Minde) wherein there is no one graine of Honeſtie, declare plainly what a ſweet Companion this is. For if a man conſider his Perſon, he ſhall finde him Lewd, Shameleſſe, a Hater mortall of all Good Men, well ſeene and practiſed in all Couzening, Legerdemaine, Coney-catching, and all other cunning Shifts, &amp; Sleights, a cracking Boaſter, Proud, Inſolent, a ſecret Back-biter, a cotentious Wrangler, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Ieſter, a Lyar, a Buſie-body, a Runnagate Wanderer, a Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Sycophant, and Trencher-Chaplaine, a couetous Exactor, and Wringer of his Patients: in a word, a Man, or rather Monſter, made
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21413:12"/>
of a Mixture of all Vices.</p>
                  <p>For hauing ſpent all his Tyme in learning theſe Feates, and long Cuſtome hauing bred an Habit or ſecond Nature, it cannot bee but that in Vertues Place there ſucceedeth a whole Troupe, and as it were a bottomeleſſe Whirlepoole of all Vice, and odious Naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Filthineſſe.</p>
                  <p>Herevpon hee neither Fearing God, nor Caring for the good Lawes of Man, (I am aſhamed to ſpeake that, which they ſhame not to commit) refuſeth not to giue Horrible and Deteſtable Counſell, for the murthering of Poore Infants in their mothers bellyes, procuring them to fall from the Tree, like vntimely Fruite. And being as laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuious as a Sparrow in the Spring, hee maketh no bones to corrupt and ſollicite to vncleanneſſe, young beautifull Maidens (hauing a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Facultie in Curing the Greene Sickneſſe) yea, and comely Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons and Wiues, if he may handſomely come into their Chambers: bluſhing no whit to ſpend many houres in Carowſing in Tauernes, and dallyance among Curtemans.</p>
                  <p>And according to the diuers Diſpoſitions and Humours of Men, that hee may fit and Pleaſe all, he layeth aſide the Behauiour and Grauitie of a Phiſition, and putteth vpon Him the Perſon of a Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, and Paraſite, making account as the World goeth, to thriue better thereby, then by his profeſſion: refuſing no Seruitude, or Drud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, how baſe ſo euer, that hee may creepe into Fauour with his Good Maiſters, and Miſtreſſes, and get into that Great Lord, or Rich La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Bookes. One while hee playeth the Apothecarie, an other while the Cooke, an other while the Seruing Man: other whiles ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth in ſtead of Mother Midnight, and ſometime hee is content to carrie the Piſſe pot, abaſing Himſelfe to euery Seruile and Slauiſh Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Nay by your leaue, Sometimes (which is of all other moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, and vnbefitting) hee playeth the Foole and Ieſter, and now and then (which is worſt of all) the Bawd and Pandore.</p>
                  <p>And he is ſo farre from being thought worſe for all this, by the Vulgars, that he is counted an Obſequious, Officious, Neat &amp; Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Man, a Merry, and good Fellow, and the Onely Phiſition.</p>
                  <p>Among other things hee laboureth to excell in Garrulitie, and much Babling: his Tongue being like a Lambs Tale, or Aſpen leafe, which neuer lyeth ſtill, but is alwayes wagging. And ſince he cannot come neare others in ſound Learning, Iudgement, and Skil in his Art, he will be ſure to goe farre beyond them in Childiſh, Fooliſh, Vnſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourie, Tedious, and Tierſome Loquacitie. So that by a vaine and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21413:13"/>
fond boaſting of Learning, and impudent promiſing, and vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king many and great Matters, he is accounted a great and profound Doctor among the rude and ignorant Multitude, eſpecially among ſimple &amp; credulous Women, (who through their weakneſſe of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhallowneſſe of Conceit, and Leuitie of Minde, are of all other moſt readie to embrace old wiues Tales, Lyes, and Forgeries) he kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth a foule Coyle, playing the Champion, and Warriour with his Tongue, vaunting aboue meaſure of his great and noble Acts, in kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling I know not how many <hi>Chymaeras;</hi> deſpiſing, &amp; that with a Grace, all the Learned Phiſitions of the Place, and ſometimes Age wherein he liueth, barking and byting, reuiling, and calumniating them, at his Pleaſure, as not worthy to carry his Bookes, or once to be named, or compared with his ſweete Selfe, our great Magnifico, and all to the end that he might alienate Mens Minds from Them, &amp; by his ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Cauils and Slaunders, impaire their Reputation, and brand them with the blacke Coale of Infamy and Reproach.</p>
                  <p>Now if by theſe cunning ſleights, vnſauourie Pratling, ſecret Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap>ation, he haue ſcraped together a few Crownes, that he may tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> into ſome forraine Countrey, hee will make ſure to fawne vpon the Female kinde, and to purchaſe the Fauour of honourable Ladies and <hi>Dianaes,</hi> with ſome rare, and pretious Gifts, ſuppoſe a peece of Counterfeit Vnicomes-horne, or a Bezoat-ſtone, made of Powder of Poſt, or glaſſie Sand, the Onely, and Soueraigne Antidote, and Medicine, (if you will beleeue my great Maiſter) of all Maladie, Treacle, Diateſſaron, or ſome Counterfeit Drugge cloſed hard with the Venetian Seale, or a litle white Clay: which hee calleth <hi>Terra Lemnia,</hi> or ſome ſuch like precious Iewell, not worth a button.</p>
                  <p>Now he impudently, with a whole ſtreame of prittle prattle, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out to the vttermoſt his goodly Gifts, that they are worth twiſe their waight in Gold: that they muſt be laid vp in their Caskets, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g their moſt coſtly Ornaments, and kept as their Life.</p>
                  <p>Thus with theſe cunning ſleights, fawnings, and flattering words, and Gifts not worth a ſtrawe, (which notwithſtanding ſilly Women haue not the wit to reiect, but take them with both hands, and locke them vp for Treaſures, extolling and praiſing them to the Skyes among their Goſſips) he winneth the Spurres among the Multitude: and being in high Admiration, Credit, and renowme with my Goſſip Prittle Prattle, his Fame is by &amp; by, ſpread through the whole Town, as with Bell and Clapper, and hee reckoned the onely Learned and profound Doctor.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21413:13"/>For he cannot poſſibly make ſo loud and impudent a Lye, but it ſtraight way runneth for currant, among theſe credulous and poore Soules. For among Blinde, the Blinker eaſily ruleth the Roſt.</p>
                  <p>So that by his lewd and lowd Lyes, and other pretie Shifts, and nimble Sleights, he bringeth to paſſe, that hee is applauded in euery Corner, and magnified by the common ſort, as an other <hi>Apollo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For they delighting altogether in Noueltie, and loathing their old accuſtomed Phyſitions, though neuer ſo learned, if there come any ſtraunge Beaſt, or Monſter, out of <hi>Barbary,</hi> or Iacke an Apes from <hi>Cataia,</hi> they doo gaze vpon him with Admiration, flocke after him by whole Troupes, and ſet him out, in higheſt Degrees of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations.</p>
                  <p>And being compaſſed with this Crew of Idiots, and ſitting in his Chaire of State with his Cap of Maintenance, by his ſilly Patient, it is a world to heare how his Tongue rowleth and walketh at randome, (but not one wiſe word, or any way appertaining to the matter, if he might gaine thereby a Kingdome.) One while with magnificall, bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſted, and ell-long words, he boaſteth of his ſtraunge and admirable Cures, (you may take time to beleeue them) an other while, he telleth endleſſe, long, and headleſſe Stories, of his rare, and hard Aduentures, in Trauailes and Perigrinations, vttering oft times, and that with great arrogancie, and ſhameleſſe Impudencie, as many Lyes, as words. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhile he taketh vp the Perſon of a leaſter, and playeth the Foole in the Play very ſingularly. For that Part of all other (as it pleaſeth himſelfe and his fond Fauourites the beſt) ſo it becommeth him right well.</p>
                  <p>But he hath one propertie, which by the way is worthy of ſpeciall Commendation. If he ſee or heare any Thing in the Houſe of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, it were as good to haue bene cryed at the Croſſe. He cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide to keepe Counſell.</p>
                  <p>For it is not poſſible that a Man of many words, ſhould haue any Truth or Secrecie in him.</p>
                  <p>And as he is a Babler, ſo is he likewiſe a good Trencher man, or Good fellow as they call them, louing company and good cheare paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing well: and the Cheſſe, the Dice, a Cup of neat Wine, better a great deale then his Booke.</p>
                  <p>For if you miſle him at any Tyme, you may be ſure to finde him either in the Tauerne, or at Bowles, or at ſome Feaſt or Meeting of Good-fellowes.</p>
                  <p>For our Smell-feaſt, will be ſure to haunt the Houſes and Tables
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21413:14"/>
of Rich and great Men, partly to fill his Paunch, and partly that he may be thought to know all faſhions, and that hauing wonne the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of Groſſe-headed and credulous Rich Capen-caters, hee may by their meanes be preferred and aduanced.</p>
                  <p>And though he make glorious &amp; vaunting Pollicitations of bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Beares, and moouing Mountaines, yet if truſting to his big and Bugge words, vpon ſome vrgent neceſſitie you deſire his Counſell in ſome ſodaine Symptom and headlong Diſeaſe, by and by you ſhall finde him falter at the firſt onſet, as a Man beſide his wit, and not knowing which way to turne himſelfe, or at what End to begin.</p>
                  <p>Then not able any longer to couer his Ignorance, he getteth into a Corner to peruſe his Note-booke, which he hath patched from ſome Apothecaries File, or elſe ſome Engliſh Pamphlet of Surgery, which he yet vnderſtands not without an Interpreter, or elſe he flieth to thoſe old S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>esbies, and Trudge blew-coats <hi>Antimony,</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitate, and if theſe good-fellowes chance to faile him, then wanting all found Learning and Iudgement, it is a Good ſport to ſee how hee ſumbleth and confoundeth himſelfe, running into twentie Errors, and Abſurdities, euery one greater then another.</p>
                  <p>So that by this meanes the Diſeaſe doth oftimes ſooner diſpatch the Patient, then our Pretie and Gay Doctor can reſolue of a Courſe to be taken.</p>
                  <p>But that nothing may be wanting to our barred Cumanyſt, hee laboureth in his Gate, Geſture, and Attire, to reſemble the right <hi>Aeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culapian:</hi> but ſo, that he is like an Ape clad in Purple, with a whole table of Toyes and Trinkets that by Gariſh, Outlandiſh, and vncouth Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, his great Gold Chaine, and gliſtering Rings vpon euery Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, he may draw to him the Concourſe, and Admiration of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and more readily vtter his Cart-load of Leaſings.</p>
                  <p>Now as this Stage like Brauery requireth no ſmall coſt: ſo doeth it greatly further our Magnifico in many Prettie and Cunning Shifts and Tricks of Gaining.</p>
                  <p>Among other Feats, if any of them is more Craftie, or hath a litle more broken Latine in his Budget, then the Common Sort, hee pryeth into the Practiſe of other Phyſitions, and layeth about dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for thoſe Medicines, which he hath heard or knowne to do good: and hauing once gotten a Tranſcript of them, hee vſeth them hand ouer head, without Art, or Reaſon.</p>
                  <p>Which notwithſtanding if wee giue credite to <hi>Herophilus,</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21413:14"/>
vnleſſe they paſſe through the Hand of Skilfull and Iuditiall Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, do more hurt then Good. That which is one Mans Bliſſe, is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mans Bane.</p>
                  <p>The greater Part of theſe Study, and that ſeriouſly, the Art of Sophiſtry, Couſening, and plaine Cony-catching, aduauncing, and ſetting to ſale with Great applauſe and Concourſe, their wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>Nostrums,</hi> which they haue patched together by the marring of two or three good Medicines, to make a third worſt of all, feeding the Common People with Toyes, Trifles, Bables, Nut-ſhels, plaine Chaffe in ſtead of Wheate, which notwithſtanding they ſet out, to the vtmoſt, with more then Hyperbolicall, or rather Paracelfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Commendations.</p>
                  <p>Thus they ineſcate and circumuent poore ſilly Soules, leauing them as much mony in their Purſes, as they haue Wit in theyr Heads: eſpecially if they prepare theyr Medicines themſelues, at home in theyr Selles, and hyre two or three Brokers, to blaze theyr Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations in euery Corner of the Citie.</p>
                  <p>And if they can perſwade them (according to the fooliſh opinion of Many) that nothing is wholeſome, effectuall and Soueraine, but that which is far fetcht and deare bought (for they fill the Purſe) they haue halfe wonne the Goale. For all ordinary and common Gifts of Nature, are deſpiſed and ſet at naught by theſe Braue Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cos, which haue nothing but Vnicornes horne, Bezoar ſtone, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtery of Pearles, and I knowe not what Precious, and Forreine Bugges and Drugges in theyr Mouthes.</p>
                  <p>Theſe our <hi>Mounts-banke</hi> proclaimeth lyke a Daw vpon a Perke, to be infallible and ſure Cardes, approoued and ratified by long and good Experience, laying oft times his Head to pawne, that they are ſuch as whereof common and triuiall Galenicall Doctors (for with that Style hee brandeth all learned Phyſitions) are altogether Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant.</p>
                  <p>Wherevpon that hee may by all meanes auoyd to treade in the ſteppes of the auncient and moderne Worthies, this blinde, and ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Impoſtor, carefully ſhunneth all benigne, ſafe, well-expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced, Iudiciall, and Rationall Medicines, and maketh choyſe, of Churliſh, Violent, Vncouth Drugges, inuented not to Purge, but to torment and excarnificat: not to ſaue, but to Kill Men, couering theyr ſtrong Poyſon, in a ſmall Doſe, giuing them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in Bozenges, ſometime in Wine, that the poore Patient, looking vppon the fayre and pleaſaunt Bayte, may not deſerye
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21413:15"/>
the Hooke and Poyſon lurking within: and all this he doth with great Boldneſſe and Impudencie, not knowing the Daunger and Perill enſuing.</p>
                  <p>For they beeing (by all Claſſicall and Rationall Phiſitions) raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the Ranke of Poyſons, do therefore violate Nature, not onely by their Quantitie, but likewiſe by their Qualitie, be their Doſe neuer ſo ſmall.</p>
                  <p>Others as blinde and bold Bayards as the former, bring out of their Budgets, and diſpearſe abroad as Soueraigne Salues, certaine Powders, Alcola, Vnguents, Cerats, Oyles, not worth a rotten threed, not knowing whereof they are compounded, and oft times being not able to Name them aright.</p>
                  <p>Other, vnder the Names and Tytles of <hi>Elixir</hi> of Lyfe, Quin-Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Gold, Pearle, Azoth, and Panacea, which they themſelues haue made, and account Secrets of Secrets (whereby they haue fetched backe I know not how many Soules embarked alreadie in <hi>Charons</hi> boate) do ſell certaine Gimmalls, with great applauſe, and for graet ſummes of money, and by their Factors diſpearſe them abroad into forraine Countries.</p>
                  <p>Others, that they may colourably and cunningly hide their groſſe Ignorance, when they know not the Cauſe of the Diſeaſe, referre it vnto Charmes, Wichcrafts, Magnificall Incantations, and Sorcerie, vainely, and with a brazen forehead, affirming that there is no way to help them, but by Characters, Circles, Figure caſtings, Exerciſmes, Coniutarions, and other Impious, and Godleſſe Meanes.</p>
                  <p>Other ſet to ſale at a great price, certaine A mulets of Gold and Siluer, ſtamped vnder an appropriate and ſelected Conſtellation of the Planets, with ſome Magicall Character, Shameleſly boaſting that they will cure all Diſeaſes, and worke I know not what other won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
                  <p>O gratefull and delightfull Comedie vnto the Diuell, whereat he is ready to burſt Himſelf with loud Laughter, to ſee how he leadeth by the Noſe the Common people, with theſe Iugling Illuſions, and Sophiſtications, and thereby greatly amplifieth and inlargeth his Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>Others ſwelling with a big conceit, and vaine oſtentation, of skill, and deepe inſight in their Facultie, by the ſole and bare Inſpection of the ſtinking Piſpot, like an old Hag, or Sorcereſſe, ſhewing great wonders in her Chriſtall Glaſſe, neuer once ſeeing the Patient, nor pondering with Iudiciall conſideration, the Indications Curatiue,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21413:15"/>
doo vnſauourly and Idly diſcourſe of the Nature, Cauſes, and Cure of Diſeaſes, before ſilly Chare-women, and ſimple Boyes and Gyrles, that in whole troupes flocke to their Houſes, with a Glaſſe Piſle-pot in their Hands: confidently auouching, or rather manifeſtly and ſhameleſly Lying, contrarie to the Part and Office of an Ingenuous and honeſt Man, that they finde out and diſcerne all theſe Things by gazing vpon the Putrified and ſtrong-ſented Vrine.</p>
                  <p>But theſe Men eſteeme Gaine to be ſweete, though it come by impudent Lying, and vnhoneſt Couzening: whereby they ſend whole Multitudes of ſilly Soules, inſnated in their Gins, vnto <hi>Plutos</hi> Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>Others moſt impudently, and falſly affirme, that all Diſeaſes and Maladies how contrarie in Nature ſo euer, may indifferently, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be cured with one Medicine, or Panacea.</p>
                  <p>And that we need not ſo many Compoſitions, and Preſcripts, as are now vſed: but that our Apothecaries may ſpare their Labour, ſhut vp their Shops, and ſeeke out ſome new Occupation, ſince it is a matter of ſmall Difficultie, to make one Cacolicke, (I ſhould haue ſaid Catholike) which may ſerue for all Turnes.</p>
                  <p>But ſince Experience hath neuer yet approued, this phantaſticall and ſenſeleſſe Fiction, of ſome crazed and addle Braine, neither Any Man made Demonſtration thereof by good and ſound Reaſon: it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth that theſe Idle and bruiſed-headed fellowes, are notable Impoſtores, Quack-ſaluers, and Such as offer moſt diſhonourable and intollerable violence to Phyſicke, and all her faire and beautifull Nymphes.</p>
                  <p>Yet the Poore and Silly Multitude admireth ſuch, as Petite <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> and <hi>Apollos,</hi> not knowing that theſe Magicall Arts, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Sleights of Legerdemaine, and plaine Coney-catching, are growne into a great Myſterie and Occupation, and in a manner the onely Way to thriue: being indeed no better then plaine Theeuing, or Robbing of men by the high way.</p>
                  <p>He therefore that hath bene trained vp in Cunning, and nimble Shifts, and Couſenings from his youth, and deſireth to fill his bagge ſpeedily, and withall to haue the ringing Name and Fame of a great and profound Phiſition, let him take Order to make his Medicines at home in a Corner, or Seller, or at leaſt giue it out, that they are ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by Himſelfe, though he ſecretly buy them abroad at the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries; or let him haue alwaies at Hand one, or at the moſt two or three Medicines (if one of them be a Charme it is no matter, but all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21413:16"/>
the better, wherewith let him promiſe Boldly, confidently, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily, without bluſhing any more then a blacke Dogge, that he will Cure all Diſeaſes whatſoeuer.</p>
                  <p>For by this meanes he ſhall be ſure to vtter his Wares at a dearer and higher rate, then Reaſon or Honeſtie would require, and to make a good round Market when other ſtand ſtill and coole theyr Heeles.</p>
                  <p>And beſide that, the Common people will flocke to ſuch a One in whole Thraues, as vnto an Oracle of <hi>Apollo,</hi> hee ſhall gaine this thereby, that neither the Patient, nor his Friends, ſhal be able to know whether in ſtead of a Soueraigne Medicine, far fet, and deare bought, they receiue rank poyſon, or at leeſt ſome vncouth, vnfitting, or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Dregge, or Drugge.</p>
                  <p>Neither neede hee to feare any ſharpe Cenſure, of his ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding Skill, and double Diligence, and leaſt being in Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with other Learned Phiſitions, he be compelled to bewray his Sottiſh and barred Ignorance, if (as the faſhion is of Men of his Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance and Coate, hee can ſet a good Face on the matter, and Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour a loud, that theſe are hidden and abſtruſe Secrets, not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to any, that they are no where to be had, eyther for Loue or Gold, but at his Houſe, or from his Apothecarie, and that no Man in the World knoweth how to turne his hand to the making of them, ſaue Himſelfe alone.</p>
                  <p>But it is one of the greateſt Miſchiefes and Miſeries in the World, that ſuch ſhould profeſſe themſelues Artiſts and Phiſitions, who know not how to performe any one Part or Office of a true &amp; worthy Phiſition.</p>
                  <p>For theſe are not the properties of any Ingenuous, Liberall, and Salutiferous Science, or Qualities of a Learned, Sufficient, and Skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Artiſt or Profeſſor, but rather euident Arguments, of a Peruerſe, Illiberall, and monſtrous Diſpoſition, thus like an Owle, or Night-Rauen, to flye, and ſhun the Light.</p>
                  <p>For it is appropriate onely to crooked, and ill mannered Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and thoſe that are altogether vnacquainted, with Humanitie, and all good Letters, to traduce and calumniate, among the rude and ſimple Idiots, the actions and workes of Cunning, and Learned Artiſts, moſt skilfully and artificially accompliſhed: and withall magnifically to extoll, and commend, with bombaſted, and tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Termes, their owne Falſe, Sophiſticate, and Adulterate Wares,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21413:16"/>
and to inuent theſe Sathanicall Deluſions, and in inexpiable Crafts, and ſubtill Deuices, to inſnare and abuſe the Simple and Common Sort.</p>
                  <p>So that by theſe Courſes they both deceiue themſelues in the end, and deceiue, delude, and abuſe others moſt Impiouſly, lewdly, and Nefariouſly.</p>
                  <p>We conclude therefore, and that as wee Suppoſe, vpon good and ſufficient Ground, that Incomparable, and Diuine <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> did moſt truly, and wiſely affirme, that there are many great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, in Name and Eſtimation of Men: but in Truth and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but very fewe, rightly deſeruing that Reputation and Style.</p>
                  <p>And that they who are Complete and accompliſhed Phiſitions, are by the Verdit and Iudgement of all the Sages, and Wiſe Men, that either haue or do liue in the World, worthy of all Honour, Praiſe, and high Eſtimation.</p>
                  <p>And theſe alone, hauing paſſed thorow the Courſe of Learning, and giuen ſufficient Teſtimony and Proofe of their ſound Skil, Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Experience, grounded vpon Reaſon, Art, and Sence, are able and fitted to exerciſe the Diuine Art of Phiſicke, to the Welfare and Health of Mankinde.</p>
                  <p>And they alone doo happily atchieue theſe three maine Scopes, of Curing Speedily, without lingring Delayes, which are worſe then a ſhort diſpatch of Death, Safely without hazarding, or running the Patients Life vpon thoſe Rockes, wherevpon the Quack-ſaluer (as an vnskilfull Pilot) doth for the moſt part moſt lamentably wracke them, pleaſantly without that loathſomeneſſe and Tediouſneſſe wherewith they are choaked by the counterfeit <hi>Mounte-banke</hi> and <hi>Slabtaker.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As for them who doo more eagerly affect and hunt after the Name of Phyſitions, then the ſubſtance and ſufficiencie, eſteeming it inough for their purpoſe, if they bee created Doctors at Dawes Croſſe, by the rude, and vnskilfull Multitude, and ſo be reputed, and paſſe Currant Phyſitions, and great Clarkes among them, who are indeed diſguiſed and counterfeit Impoſtors, Iuglers, and Couzeners, they ſhould bee rightly ſerued, and the Weale-pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, Prudently and Religiouſly prouided for, if they ſhould bee interdicted to practiſe that Art which they neuer learned: or in imitalatio of <hi>Cato Cenſorininus,</hi> proſcribed, baniſhed, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by whole Troupes out of thoſe Cities and Prouinces, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they haue neſtled, or at the leaſt ſhould bee puniſhed for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21413:17"/>
their vnbridled and intollerable Boldneſſe, in Butchering, and Excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicating Mens Bodies, according to the Nature and Qualitie of their Offence.</p>
                  <p>That by this meanes they might be reſtrained and reduced into their proper Ranke, and Order, &amp; not through Polypragmony, which is the Companion of Ignorance, Well ſpring of Diſorder and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and common Peſt of Mankinde, buſily intrude themſelues, and thruſt in their Sickle into other Mens Harueſt.</p>
                  <p>So it would come to paſſe, that Honeſt, Good, and Learned Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, ſhould not vndergo a moſt Vniuſt, &amp; Vnworthy Conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that is, in beholding daily Knaues, Couzening Shifters, and ranke Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, preferred before them, or at leaſt equally valued, eſteemed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected: and that Gate and Gap would be ſhut and ſtopped, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by theſe blind Buzzards, and bold Bayards, theſe butcherly Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores, doo freely enter to excruciat their poore Patients, and kill Men without controllment.</p>
                  <p>But a good Magiſtrate, to whom nothing is more deare &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, then the ſafegard both of the Goods, and Perſons of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, is alwayes a Louer and Fauourer of Learning, and Liberall Arts, a Patron, and Mecaenas of Learned Men, and therefore in his Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, vertuous Diſpoſition, and watchfull Care for the Common Good, prouideth by all meanes, that no Man be wronged or wracked in his Eſtate or Perſon, and preuenteth all Occaſions, of ſuch Schythi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, or rather Sathanicall torturing and maſſacring of Men.</p>
                  <p>But he that Winketh, and looketh thorow the Fingers at theſe matters, and like a ſleeping and drowſie Shepheard, letteth the Raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Wolfe at his pleaſure, pray vpon the poore Sheepe, cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be excuſed among the vertuous. For that euill and corrupt Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, which hath euery where preuailed, redounding greatly to the ruine and Confuſion of Mankinde, can by no meanes free the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate from blame. Nay it rather argueth, and conuinceth both the Practiſer, Conſenter, and Conniuer, at ſuch horrible Crimes (for a ſmall and baſe Bribe) to be worthy of the ſame Puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>But they who are altogether Illiberall, Vnlettered, and Slaues to abſurd, and erronious Opinions, loathing, and proſecuting with Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinian hatred, all True and Learned Phiſitions, nay Truth and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it ſelfe, haue this bred in the Bones, and rooted in the Fleſh, through the Crooked peruerſitie of their Diſpoſitions, and Ruditie of their Wits, to barke againſt Learned Men, and their wholſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, and honeſt Courſes, and to be delighted with monſtrous, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21413:17"/>
vncouuth Conceits, or rather Deceits, and with ſuch ſottiſh and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Quackſaluers; who are worthy to fall into the hands of theſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Impoſtors, ſo well fitting their Humours, that according to the Old Saying, Like Lips may be ſerued with like Lettuce.</p>
                  <p>But theſe grand Seniors ſhould do farre better if they imployed their ſwelling and high Conceit of deepe Wiſdome in their owne Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and containe themſelues within their Shops and Ware-houſes, and not arrogate to themſelues, to Iudge of Matters whereof they are altogether ignorant, (it belonging to Artiſt to Iudge of Art) leaſt they be compelled to heare againſt their Will, That the Shoomaker muſt not meddle beyond his Shooe.</p>
                  <p>Now (thou blinde Empericke, and vaine-vaunting <hi>Mountebanke,</hi> whoſoeuer thou art) let me in Concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, intreat thee, to learne by this ſhort Diſcourſe, this ſhort Leſſon, To Know thy ſelfe, which though it be briefe, yet is it the Chiefe, and Choyſe of all other Documents.</p>
                  <p>Dwell with thy Selfe, and breake not thy Ranke, but keepe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Compaſſe, and thou ſhalt eaſily perceiue thine owne Pouertie, Want, and Weakneſſe.</p>
                  <p>I for my part, wiſh thee from my Heart, a more ſound Head, and honeſt Heart, that thou mayeſt either fundamentally learne the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Excellent Art of Phyſicke, and proceed in thy Cures by a certaine and right Lyne and Method, without fooliſh Superſtition, or wicked Impoſture, or elſe that thou wouldeſt honeſtly giue ouer that learned Profeſſion, till <hi>Apollo</hi> haue more clearly enlightned thee, with his ſhyning and bright beames, leaſt to thy indeleble Ignominy, Shame, and Reproach, ſome wiſe Man pronounce againſt thee this Sentence: That thou art either an Aſſe, a Foole, or a Cony-catcher.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Be Bold and Conſtant in well dooing: for when all is done, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie will in the end, obtaine the Victorie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21413:18"/>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21413:18"/>
            <head>A diſcouery of certaine Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems, whereby our Engliſh Emperickes haue bene obſerued ſtrongly to oppugne, <hi>and oft times to expugne their poore Patients Purſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T cannot be ſufficiently lamented, that the moſt auncient, worthy, and honourable Profeſſion of Phyſicke, which hath bene in preceding Ages, a Colledge of learned, graue, and profound Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, is now become the Common Inne, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacle, and Sanctuarie of Make-ſhifts, Banker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupts, and Impoſtors. <hi>Fuit Honos Medicinae apud Seclum prius.</hi> Tyme was, when that diuine, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Science was had in high, and yet due Admiration, Honour, and Reputation. <hi>Salomon</hi> the moſt wiſe, rich, and renowmed Prince that the world (from her <hi>Alpha</hi> to her <hi>Omega)</hi> hath yeelded, diſdai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned not the Contemplation and Studie of this noble and diuine Art. Nay which is more, did illuſtrate Phyſicke with his writings, and compoſed a great Volume of the Nature, of Byrds, Beaſts, Trees, and Hearbes, deſcribing them, from the Cedar in <hi>Libanus,</hi> to the Hyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſope that groweth on the wall.</p>
            <p>This excellent and incomparable Worke, to the vnſpeakeable griefe, and invaluable loſſe of all <hi>Aeſculapians,</hi> is periſhed in the deepe Sea-gulfe of Antiquitie, which hath ſwallowed vp, deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and conſumed the Monuments of many Worthies. <hi>Mythri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates</hi> that puiſſant King of <hi>Pontus,</hi> who was for many yeares terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the World-conquering Romaines, amiddeſt his Martiall and Kingly affaires, ſpent no ſmall time in Phyſicall Meditations: erecting to himſelfe by the Compoſition of one Medicine, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, durable, and admirable a Trophee, as <hi>Pompey</hi> the great did, by his Victory againſt him.</p>
            <p>In this Kings Cloſet were found by that Noble Romaine, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Bookes written with his owne hand, both of the vertues of Plants, and Conſtitution of Mans Body, highly valued by that worthy <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor Euax</hi> a King of <hi>Arabia,</hi> wrote a Booke of <hi>Botanologye,</hi> which hee dedicated to the Emperour <hi>Nero.</hi> It is reported by Hiſtorians, that in auncient Tymes there was no King, either of <hi>Aegypt, Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21413:19"/>
or <hi>Arabia,</hi> who did not himſelfe either write ſomewhat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Art of Phyſicke, or at leaſt by his Kingly bountie, and large Penſions, encouraged others to imploy their Heads and Wits in that Studie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zenophon</hi> bringeth in <hi>Cyrus,</hi> conferring and diſcourſing with a Phyſition, as a fit Colloqunter for a Prince, about the hidden Secrets, and deepe Miſteries of Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> that matchleſſe and inuincible Romane Emperour, made a Decree, that all Profeſſors of Phyſicke ſhould be free Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and Burgeſſes of <hi>Rome. Democides</hi> the Phyſition was in ſuch credit and authoritie with <hi>Darius</hi> the Perſian, that hee had a place aſſigned at his Table, and was as it were fellow-Commoner with him. <hi>Ataxerxes</hi> hauing ſent for <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and being denied with griefe and anger, threatned a reuenge againſt all <hi>Greece.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſclepiades</hi> reiected <hi>Mithridates</hi> Meſſengers, and refuſed all his liberall and Princely Offers. <hi>Eraſistratus</hi> the Phiſition, receiued for a reward at one Tyme, of King <hi>Ptolomye,</hi> (ur as others write of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus)</hi> an hundred Talents: which amounteth in our Money, to ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thouſand Crownes.<note place="margin">Plin. <hi>21.</hi> li. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stertinius</hi> complained of the Princes of his Dayes, becauſe his ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend for reading Phyſicke, was but fiue hundred thouſand Ceſterties. This is eſteemed 4150. pound &amp; two ſhillings, foure penee, wheras he gained more by his practiſe in the Citie. The like ſtipend was giuen by <hi>Claudius Caeſar</hi> to this mans Brother. <hi>Trinas</hi> the Maſſilian left an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand Seſtertyes by Legacie, to build the walles of his Citie. I forbeare to ſhewe their great fauour, credit, and authoritie with mightie Potentates and Princes, as <hi>Philip</hi> with <hi>Alexander, Muſa</hi> with <hi>Augustus.</hi> I omit the Aruncians, Albutians, Rubrians, Laſſians, and Carpentans, whoſe ſtipend in <hi>Rome</hi> was 205. Aureos. <hi>Thaddaeus</hi> the Florentine when he rode abroad, receiued ordinarily for his Fee, 500. Crownes a day: and for one Cure vpon <hi>Honorius</hi> the Pope, ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crownes at a clap. <hi>Comineus</hi> the French <hi>Thucydides,</hi> telleth of a Phiſition of <hi>Ludouic</hi> the 11. French King, who had from the King, admirable, and almoſt incredible Fees and rewards. To paſſe by theſe, with many other famous Preſidents of Antiquitie, clearly demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Worlds view, the true and due worth and eſteeme, of this excellent Profeſſion, to the ſtaine and bluſh of our preſent Age, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth infinitly for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation of Phiſicke, that the Meſſias &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of the world, the <hi>Emmanuel,</hi> God, it is the Lord Ieſus himſelfe in the daies of his ſoiourning, &amp; walking here vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Earth, (refuſing to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21413:19"/>
intermeddle with deciding of Controuerſies, &amp; diuiding of Lands and Goods, did notwithſtanding ſpend a good part of his Tyme (after the performance of his Propheticall office in teaching and curing the Soules of Men) in healing the Diſeaſes and Maladyes of their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: that is, in plaine termes, in exerciſing the Office &amp; Function of the Phyſition. But here me thinks before I proceed further in this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, one ioggeth me on the elbow with this item. A Sophiſter of <hi>Greece</hi> made a long Oration in praiſe of <hi>Hercules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One ſtanding by, before he could pronounce the whole, cut him off thus. <hi>Quis (quaeſo) vnquam Herculem vituperauit?</hi> In like ſort a man may demaund of you, who haue begun a Panegyrick of Phyſicke. I pray you (Syr) who euer in his right wits diſpraiſed Phyſicke? Well I could (if I were diſpoſed) anſwere this <hi>Quaere.</hi> But I will bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for this Tyme to take it for graunted, that no Man of Common Sence, Wit, Reaſon, Iudgement, Diſcretion, Learning, or Humanitie, will euer open his Mouth in diſpraiſe of a Profeſſion ſo auncient, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, beneficiall, and neceſſarie vnto Mankinde, (without which, neither Theologie can often preuaile to reforme the vicious Minde, vnleſſe Medicine diſpoſe the Body, and contemper the Humours: and Lawe ſhould commaund in vaine, if Phyſicke did not yeeld apt and able Bodyes to obey) I will drawe nearer to my preſent Purpoſe: wherevnto I hope this ſhort Praelude in Phiſickes Praiſe, will proue nothing impertinent. For if Phyſicke be of that worth, honour and reputation (as hath bene in part touched, and might haue bene more amply declared, but that with the Dogge of <hi>Egypt,</hi> I am conſtrained to take a ſnatch and away) then, intollerable are the Indignities, and exceeding great are the Iniuries, which theſe baſe Cullions, and Buz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardly Venturers, (for ſo I chuſe rather to terme them, with a Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Man of our Colledge, then Emperickes) who leaping from theyr Shopboords, and leauing their Mechanicall Trades, haue, and doo daily offer to that faire, goodly, and gallant Lady. A Fardell and Packe of the deceitfull Wares, and ſubtill Sophiſtications of theſe Circumferaneous luglers, hath alreadie bene vnfolded and laid open in the former Treatiſe, written in Latine by a learned Germaine. Now giue me leaue, to acquaint you with ſome ſuch cunning Sleights, and pretie tricks of Legerdemaine, which I haue obſerued to be put in vſe and practiſe by our London Interlopers, and Quack-ſaluers, wherby diuers honeſt Men and Women, haue bene notoriouſly abuſed, delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, emunged of their Money, and plainly coney catched.</p>
            <p>The cunning and ſlye Deuiſes, ſubtill Policies, and Warre-like
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21413:20"/>
Stratagems, whereby theſe valerous Thraſoes, and great Magnificoes doo lay a ſtraight ſiege, and make many ſtrong aſſaults vpon their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients Purſes (for vnto the poore Purſe is all the Quarell) haue partly reſpect vnto Themſelues, and partly vnto their Patient.</p>
            <p>The firſt Proiect reſpecting Themſelues, whereby they ayme to winne credit with the Patient, and inſinuate themſelues into his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, bringing him into a Fooles-paradiſe, and cauſing him to haue their perſons in high admiration, is to blowe into his Eares, and that with a ſhameleſſe impudent face, and a tedious multitude of vaine, lying, and vaunting words, that they haue certaine hidden, deepe, and precious Secrets, altogether vnknowne to the Galeniſts, and Schoole-Doctors, whereby they are able to worke wonders, and to quell <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantua</hi> himſelfe. If the Patient demaund how they came by this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found knowledge, hauing neuer followed the courſe of Learning, or ſtudied in any Vniuerſitie: then they eyther begin with a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne grace, and ſet countenance, a long Storie of a written Booke of moſt rare and admirable Medicines, inuented by a certaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, and deepe learned Fryar or Monke, and hidden with great care, in the Wall, or Sellar of a Monaſterie: Which Booke by great Chaunce, and their happy Fortune, hauing come to their hands, they would not part with it for Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Cope, or a Kings Raunſome. Or elſe you ſhall haue a Tale of <hi>Manardes</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> great Phyſition of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who keeping a ſecret Booke of moſt tare and excellent Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations, your braue and vaunting Quack-ſaluer, auouching himſelfe to haue bene his Man, will boldly (bluſhing as much as a blacke <hi>Dog</hi>) affirme vnto you, that beeing with him in his ſickneſſe, whereof he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and obſeruing diligently the place, where <hi>Manardes</hi> laid vp his Iewell, they cunningly after his Death, ſeized on this Booke, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueied it away with them. Hereby they are made of vnlettered Idiots, great and skilfull <hi>Aeſculapians,</hi> and vndertake the Cure of all ſtrange, difficult, and deadly Maladyes. Or if the Patient miſſe of theſe Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Fictions, he may well ſtumble vpon that good fellow, who (as it is ſaid) hath a long Diſcourſe of <hi>Seuerinus</hi> the Dane his ſonne, who being in ſeruice in the Spaniſh <hi>Armado, Anno.</hi> 88. was wracked and caſt on Shore. Herevpon, wandering as a poore harbourleſſe, and ſuccourleſſe Straunger, he arriued at the laſt at the houſe of our <hi>Iuppi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Hospitalis,</hi> who receiuing him into home and harbour, vſing him kindly, and at his departure furniſhing him with ſome ſupply of Pence, that thankefull Mercurie, in recompence of this great Hoſpitalitie and Humanitie, beſtowed vpon him his <hi>Caducean</hi> Rodde,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21413:20"/>
or Booke of rare Phyſicall Myſteries, whereby in an inſtant hee was from a ſilly Sot, not able to ſpeake one word of congruous La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, preſently Metaphorphoſed into a graue, demure, and grand Doctor, and Maiſter in Phyſicke. A hundred to one, if hee hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen not on ſome one or other of theſe ſtale Ieaſts, or at the leaſt, ſome other of the like Nature: Which notwithſtanding, a great Number of our Common Ones doo as readily beleeue, as if they ſhould heare the Story of S. <hi>Francis</hi> out of <hi>Legenda Aurea.</hi> And here by the way, it is worth our obſeruation, that thoſe graund Maiſters do vtterly renounce and diſclaime Learning, and all Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any Vniuerſitie, wherein it is like they neuer came (vnleſſe to ſet vp their horſe in an Inne, whileſt they breake their faſt) flying to a written Booke, or ſome Medicines, receiued from a Friend by Tradition. And would a Man imagine that any ſhould bee ſo voyd of common Sence, Reaſon, or Iudgement, as to thinke that a fewe ſcribled Receipts in an olde Moath-eaten paper ſhould make a Phyſition? Why then euery one that hath lying by him, a good Booke of Lawe, as <hi>Rastalls</hi> Statutes, or <hi>Littletons</hi> Tenures, is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Lawyer. And hee that hath two or three Bookes of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in his Houſe, is an abſolute Diuine, and may ſtep vp into the Pulpit. If this were ſo, we might well ſay with that merry Phiſition, that it had raigned Doctors in all Faculties.</p>
            <p>Their ſecond Engine, or Plauſible perſwaſiue Motiue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they labour to faſten the former Nayle, to winne Reputation of deepe Skill to themſelues, and purchaſe credite to their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naceas, and wonder-working Dregges, is a pretie figment, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, not vnlike the firſt. After they haue laide the former ground, and perceiue the poore Patient to giue a liſtening Eare to theyr forged Fable, conceiuing hope of luckie ſucceſſe, and by his nibling at the baite, that hee is like to ſwallow the hooke, they proceede to Gull him thus. They begin, to make theyr former matter good, with incredible boldneſſe and impudencie, to auerie that theyr knowledge is ſo ſingular, theyr ſecret Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaments ſo ſoueraigne, and of ſuch admirable Efficacie, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Learned and Profeſſed Phyſitions, of great Note and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, haue ſought earneſtly, Wooed, and Sollicited: nay offered good ſummes of money, to haue them imparted and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it is ſinne to belye the Diuell, and ſome Men may
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21413:21"/>
thinke I wrong them with ſo deepe a charge, I aſſure you vpon my credit, I ſpeake no more then I haue heard <hi>Hiſce Auribus.</hi> One baſe Thick-skin (whoſe Story it may be you ſhall haue hereafter more at large) taking vpon him to cure an incurable Diſeaſe, and being willed by a Phiſition, requeſted by the Patient to ioyne with him, to make knowne his Medicine. My Medicine (quoth hee) with great indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that I will not for any Mans pleaſure. D. <hi>Dodcin,</hi> and D. <hi>Caſo</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> haue offered me fortie pounds yearely during my life, if I would acquaint them with that ſecret. This was as true as that the Sea was on Fire, and this good fellow quenched it with a Bale of Flaxe. Neuertheleſſe, by this and ſuch like pretie ſleights, he carried away the Patient for that Time, and got ſome Crownes: the other Phiſition, becauſe he refuſed to hold the Candle to ſo baſe and blinde a Companion, being reiected.</p>
            <p>An other <hi>Medicastra,</hi> a tatling Goſſip, (for ſuch likewiſe haue learned their Leripoope, and haue as glib, ſmooth, &amp; nimble Tongues as the beſt) hauing commended a Drench ſhe had for an old Cough, vnto the Skyes, auerred boldly in the hearing of a Phiſition, that her Medicine was of ſuch vertue, and had done ſo great Acts, that D. <hi>Smyth</hi> and D. <hi>Turner,</hi> had taken her aſide, and with many faire words, putting likewiſe ſome Angels into her fiſt, had intreated her, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to them her Secret. But (ſaid ſhe) with a grace I warrant you, Should I teach the Doctors? nay I will neuer do it. They would make 20. or 30. pound yearely of it, whereas I do good therewith, and take ſmall recompence for my paines. The Phyſition ſmyling, anſwered. I beleeue you (good woman) that you will not teach the Doctors, I will be your warrant for that matter, you ſhall need no further Bond or Suretie. Was not this a goodly ſweete Parrate trowe yee? Haue not the Doctrs cauſe to lament that they ſhall want the inſtruction of ſuch a Lamia?</p>
            <p>A third, as bold and blinde an Empericke as London hath yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded theſe many yeares, beeing by the Coll. committed to priſon for his notorious ſottiſhneſſe, Impudency, and manifold Miſdemeanours, (to giue them the leaſt and loweſ terme) gaue it out among his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low priſoners, and ſuch as celected vetrum, that his commitment was, becauſe he refuſed to diſcloſe vnto the Phyſitions, his hidden ſecrets, whereby hee performed ſuch Cures, as they were not able to turne their hands too. But ſuppoſe wee ſhould graunt vnto theſe Bragga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docian Theſſali, that they had ſecret and good Medicines, yea ſuch as diuers Phyſitions deſired to knowe; would it therefore follow that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21413:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
they were fit Men to take vpon them the Profeſſion, and Practiſe of Phyſicke? Nothing leſſe. For Phyſicke is a great Lady or Princeſſe, hauing ſubiect vnto her, many large, goodly, and ſpacious Territories. Whereof the skill of inuenting, and making a Medicine, is one of the laſt, and leaſt in Eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So that a Man may be ſomewhat acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this Region, and yet altogether ignorant in the ample and rich Countries and Fields of Phiſicke.</p>
            <p>Phiſicke is defined by <hi>Galen</hi> in his <hi>Arte Parua:</hi> The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of things wholſome, vnwholſome, or neutrall. Or, the Science of Things Naturall, Preternaturall, and contrarie to Nature. <hi>Phyſiologye</hi> the firſt Part of Phyſicke, chalengeth for her Patrimony, thoſe ſeuen Things whereof our Nature conſiſteth: Elements, Temperaments, Humours, Spirits, Parts, Faculties, and Functions. Here is a large walke for our ſilly Emperickes, as vncouth, and vnknowne to them, as <hi>Terra-America, China,</hi> or <hi>Guiana,</hi> to our poore Plough men. Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy being but one Shyre, Prouince, or Countie, in this Precinct or Countrie, diſcourſing vpon the Parts, whereof we conſiſt, is of ſuch Nobleneſſe, Amplitude, and Reputation, as that many worthy, and excellent Wits haue bene content here to take vp their Reſt, and dwel therein their whole Time.</p>
            <p>A number of our iolly Quack-ſaluers, are ſo ignorant of this Skill, that they know not whether Anatomy be a Man or Woman, an Horſe, or a Cow. And yet it is as poſſible, for him to be a Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that neuer knew or ſawe Diſſection, as for him to be a good Carpenter, that neuer ſawe an Houſe, or a good Marriner, that neuer ſet eye on a Ship, in his Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hygicina</hi> the ſecond part of Phyſicke, trauelleth in preſeruing the health of thoſe who haue obtained a ſound Temperament, in their Similar parts, and right Proportion in the Inſtrumentall, by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and well ordered vſe of thoſe ſixe Things, which we call Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternaturall. The knowledge of thoſe Things, which we call Vnwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome: or contrarie to Nature, if you reſpect the Theorie, is termed Pathologye, and intreateth at large of the Cauſes, Signes, and Nature of Diſeaſes. If you regard the Praxis, it is termed <hi>Therapentice,</hi> who grapleth with Natures Enemie, and oppoſeth vnto all Maladies, apt, Artificiall, and Rationall Medicines, and that in three large Differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The firſt is called the Dyet of the ſicke: the ſecond, Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery: the third, <hi>Pharmacentice.</hi> So that the Phyſition, as a great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder, hath as ſubordinate to him, the Cookes for Dyet, the Surgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for manuall Operation, the Apothecaries for confecting, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21413:22"/>
Medicines. You ſee then, how goodly large, and ample Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony Phyſick hath, and that all her Store, and Skill, conſiſteth not in compounding and mingling of a Medicine. If that were all, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all our skilful Chirurgions, and Apothecaries (of whom we haue many in this Citie) ſhould be abſolute, and compleat Phyſitions, who I dare boldly affirme knowe moe and better Medicines, then the braueſt, and Crakingeſt <hi>Mounte-banke</hi> in the Land. And yet how farre the cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningeſt of them are, from being able to giue counſell in Phyſicke, both themſelues will ingeniouſly and freely acknowledge, and all men of Iudgement, may eaſily diſcerne. But who ſo bolde as blind Bayard, who ſeeing not the Daunger, and Diche before him, ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth on without feare, and plungeth himſelfe ouer Head and Eares, ere hee be aware. <hi>Herophilus</hi> calleth Medicines <hi>Manus Deorum,</hi> being preſcribed and accommodated by the learned Phyſition, but flat Poyſons if they come thorow the handes of vnlearned and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Quack-ſaluers. <hi>Nullus Morbus idem omnibus:</hi> No Diſeaſe is of the ſame Nature in all Conſtitutions. <hi>Nullum Remedium evn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem vim habet in ſingulis.</hi> No Remedie hath the lyke Operation in euery particular Patient. A good Remedie in the Head or Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet of an vnskilfull, and venterous Periclitator, is as a Sword in the handes of a mad-Man. Or as the blinde Mans ſtaffe, which may ſo fall, as it may kill the Hare. So theyr miſapplyed and miſhapen Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, may ſometime quell the Diſeaſe, but by as great chaunce and miſfortune, as that good Fellow had, who being drunke and on horſebacke, ridde in the night ſafely ouer a foote-bridge, croſſing a broad and deepe Riuer, it beeing a thouſand pounde to a Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell, that both hee and his Horſe ſhould haue come ſhort Home. <hi>Natura est Curatrix Morborum.</hi> Nature her ſelfe is the Curer of diuers Diſeaſes, into whoſe harueſt theſe intruding Copes mates do thruſt theyr Sickle, reaping oft times her due Praiſe and Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations.</p>
            <p>To conclude this Poynt, (wherein I haue beene content to dwell the longer, becauſe it is the ſtrongeſt Caſtle and Hold, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our Maiſter-Emperickes doo moſt truſt, and wherevnto they haue continuall Reſuge and Retreat in all aſſaultes) I dare boldly ſet downe this Maxime, and Theorem, and maintaine the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Commers, that <hi>Morbi curantur magis Methodo, quam Medicina.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſeaſes are rather cured by a Rationall Methode grounded
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21413:22"/>
vpon Arts Indications, then by force of any Remedie, though neuer ſo ſoueraigne. The Indications whereby Iudiciall and Rationall Phyſitions are guided and directed (as by <hi>Ariadnaees</hi> threed) in the Curation of Diſeaſes, are many, (and not to be ſtood vpon at this Tyme) all of them neglected, and vnknowne to the poore blinde Emperickes. And yet the Poet could ſay, ſpeaking but of one of them.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Temporibus medicina valet data Tempore proſunt,</l>
               <l>Sed data non apto Tempore Vina nocent.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But hauing (as I hope) ſufficiently battered this Fort, and ferri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe Coney-catching Companions from their Sanctuarie, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fox-hole, I will proceed, or rather poſt vnto their third Topi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Place, or Latebra Sophiſtica, whereby they ſeeke to mount vpon the Banke of Fame, and raiſe vp Themſelues in the Conceit of their ſimple Patients.</p>
            <p>When they perceiue the Patient to haue ſwallowed the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Flyes, then they begin to ſtand vpon theyr Typtoes, and with a compoſed Countenance, and Stagge-like geſture, to relate ſuch ſtraunge, vncouth, lowde ringing, and Paradoxicall Narrations, as a man would ſuppoſe they were ſolemnly ſet to lye for the Whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi adbibit plus paulò ſua mihi quae narrat Facinora.</hi> When they are ſet vpon theyr Ale-bench, (for it is worth noting by the way, that eyther at the Ale-houſe or Tauerne, where is their chiefe Haunt, theyr matches for Cures are vſually made) and are a little whitled, it is wonderfull, what fabulous Tales and Stories, what vnſauorie and odious Leaſings they will tell of theyr incredible, and admirable Curations, performed vppon moſt deſperate, and deadly Sickneſſes, and ſuch Perſons as were altogether giuen o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and forſaken, as forlorne and paſt helpe by the Phyſitions. There you ſhall heare of Dropſies, dead Palſies, (as they tearme them, olde and knottie Gouts, Apoplexies, great and growne Stones in the Bladder, a great rabble moe of Churliſh and Sturdie Companions, all bowing the knee, vayling the Bonnet, and dooing lowe obeyſance to our grand Seignior, Magnifico, <hi>Mounſier Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:21413:23"/>And leaſt you ſhould call in Queſtion the credit of thoſe good old Gentlemen, or doubt of the Truth of their Poeticall, Hyberbolicall, and extrauagant Diſcourſes, you ſhall haue them name the Cities and Townes, Parties, and Places where their great myraculous Workes and Wonders were acted and executed: Marry they wil be ſure not to name any Parties or Places too neare at hand (for that might perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture marre all) the fooles are more wiſe then ſo. But if you would finde out the cettaintie of theſe Matters, you may perhaps ryde your horſe out of breath Some of them will haue for their Aſſociate, an old Weather-beaten Broking Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſomewhat known to the Patient, (as very a &amp;c. as themſelues) who ſhall play <hi>Gnathos</hi> part, ſoothing them vp in all their loud Leaſings. His maner is, to ſcratch and clawe our Magnifico by the Elbow, and to tolle on the ſilly Patient, in this ſort. (Syr) vpon my credit, this is an honeſt and ſimple-meaning Gentleman, if he ſay the word, you may be bold to build and write vpon it. He would not tell you an vntruth (I dare ſay and ſweare too for a need) if he might gaine thereby an hundred pounds. Though he goe but plaine, yet his Reputation is good in the Towne and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey where he dwelleth. He is ſought vnto farre and neare. He is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with diuers Noble men, and great Perſonages, and hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe vnto them, and is admitted into Ladies Chambers, when your gay Doctors with their veluet Ierkins are ſhut out of Doores, to coole their heeles. He hath bene a Traueller in his Dayes, and hath there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by attained ſuch deepe and profound skill in Phyſicke, and ſuch rare and precious Medicines, that hee putteth downe all the Doctors where euer he commeth. Vpon my knowledge, he hath cured them, which had bene with all the Doctors in London, and ſpent great ſummes of money, without receiuing any good, till they met with him. I may ſay to you, he is the oddeſt Man in a Land. If he vndertake you, I will bee his warrant that hee will cure you. I neuer knew him yer to faile in any. He hath the Luckyeſt hand in a Countrey. I neuer knew any miſcarrie vnder it. Doth not this ſlye, and ſubtill Pricker tell a ſmooth Tale, to couer and colour this pack of cloaked Knauery? And no maruell. For he ſpeaketh and pleadeth for his Fee, and Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with his Maiſter <hi>Thraſo Mounſier Magnifico,</hi> hauing ſometimes a Proctors, ſometimes a Councellors Paye for his labour. Thus theſe two Veterators, or Couzening Copſemates act their Parts, as it were on a Stage, circumuenting and inſnaring ſimple Men and Women, altogether vnacquainted with theſe quaint Deuiſes, laughing them to come behinde their backes, ryding them for Aſſes, boaſting of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21413:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
their fiye and cunning conueyance of their matters, and each of them vaunting that he played his Part beſt. In this ſort do they ſolace them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with their ſweete ſtolen Bread, and make merry with their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients money. For you muſt vnderſtand, that vſually it purchaſeth nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Houſe, Goods, nor Lands, but a fewe Pots of the beſt Ale or Wine in the Towne. And yet they receiue moe Crownes oft times for one of their Couzenages, (for Cures I will neuer call them) then diuers learned and honeſt Phyſitions, for two or three, iuditially, and happily performed Curations.</p>
            <p>Hauing now courſarily paſſed ouer the firſt Kinde of the warre-like Engines, whereby being raiſed vpon the Mount of their owne Praiſe and Fame, theſe braue Pot-ſouldiers doo make a fierce and ſtrong batterie vpon the ſilly Patients Purſe: I will proceed to the ſecond Ranke, of militarie Statagems, and Warre-like Policies, by which they doo eft-ſoones, feale the Walles, enter the Ramperts, and like valiant, and victorious Conquerors, poſſeſſe them of the Piece and Fort, holding out againſt their matchleſſe Puiſſance.</p>
            <p>As the former had reſpect vnto themſelues, and their owne Fame and Reputation: So theſe laſt haue Reference and Relation wholly to their Patients Good.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore (let the Diſeaſe be what it will or ſhall) (for if you will haue the Truth, for the moſt part they care not, nor know not) neuer ſo daungerous, deadly, deſperate, incurable, they will promiſe moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidently and arrogantly, a perfect, abſolute, &amp; compleat Cure. All is fiſh with them that commeth to Net. They make no bones at it. And yet the Poet could ſay thus much.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Non eſt in Medico ſempèr releuctur vt Aeger.</l>
               <l>Interdum docta plus valet Arte Malum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> the Father of Phyſicke, and Phoenix of the World, whoſe Writings are by venerable Antiquitie eſteemed Oracles, and not words of Humane Tongue: who (as <hi>Macrobius</hi> ſaith) could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deceiue, nor be deceiued, whoſe Humanitie and Benignitie was ſuch, that hee knew nothing, but that hee would wee ſhould likewiſe knowe, whoſe deepe reach, inſight, and admirable Skill was ſo great, that no Man after him, knew any thing, whereof he was igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, this honourable Dictator of Phyſicke affirmeth often, that there are many Diſeaſes incurable. This commeth to paſſe, partly becauſe ſome diſeaſes are hereditary a <hi>Semine Paterno,</hi> and beeing bred in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21413:24"/>
bone, as we ſay, will hardly bee rooted out of the fleſh: partly by the Furie and Violence of ſome Maladie and <hi>Symptoms,</hi> far ſurmounting Natures ſtrength. And that appeareth eyther by the Nobilitie, and Neceſſitie of the Parte offended, or the Worthineſſe and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the Action violated, or by the euill Nature, and ſecret Malignitie of the Affect. Herevpon it is that <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> ſaith: <hi>Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere fortem Apoplexiam impoſſibile, leuem haud facile.</hi> And that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the Dignitie of the Part affected, the neceſſary vſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the Actions of Sence and Motion, mightily oppugned, and the boyſterous, and churliſh Violence of that moſt terrible and deadly Diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>Herevpon likewiſe that honourable old man, the Mirrour of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, in the ſame Book of <hi>Aphoriſmes,</hi> which hath merited the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Place among humane Writings. <hi>Aphor.</hi> 1. ſayth. <hi>O portet non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Medicum ſuum, officium facere, ſed etiam Aegrum, &amp; Aſtantes, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna eſſe rite comparata.</hi> The Phyſition muſt not onely performe his office, but the ſicke Man and his Miniſters muſt do their Parts, and outward Things muſt be well diſpoſed. This golden Sentence ſet in the Fore-front of that Diuine worke, giueth vs plainly to vnderſtand, that all the Keyes of Curation hang not at the Phyſitions Gyrdle; it reſteth not wholly and ſolely in him, to performe the Cure, but Patients and Nurſes haue likewiſe their Offices and Charges to looke vnto, and externall Accidents may marre all the Market. <hi>Morbi ſua Natura curabiles, ſaepe Patientium &amp; Clinicaram niſcitia, incuria, inobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientia, aut moroſitate incurabiles redduntur.</hi> This was the cauſe why <hi>Galen</hi> wiſheth Phyſitions neuer to meddle with thoſe who are intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, and wholly addicted to ſatisfie theyr Appetite, and ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all Delights: for (ſayth he) neither ſhalt thou reape credit, not they any good or benefite by Phyſicke. A great Emperour brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with him to a ſicke Courtier, two of his Phyſitions, demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of them what they Iudged of the ſickneſſe, whether it were cure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, or no? The firſt anſwered, that it was cureable. The other that he Iudged it incureable. I (ſayeth the Emperour) what is the Reaſon of this Diſſention and Difference betwixt you? No diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence (my Lord) anſwered the later Phiſition. <hi>Ille enim ad Rem respicit, Ego ad hominem.</hi> He reſpected, in his anſwere, the Diſeaſe, and I the Patient, whom I know to bee ſo vnruly and intemperate, that it is not poſſible to Cure him. How ignorant, vnruly, indiſcreet, and vntractable, that I ſay not peeuiſh and peruerſe many Patients are, it is too well knowne to Phyſitions, and Others likewiſe who are
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21413:24"/>
not too too exceeding partiall, and therefore needleſſe and tedious for me to ſtand vpon it. The manifold Errors and Miſdemeanours of the friends of Patients, eſpecially Women, Nurſe-keepers, Seruants, Cookes, Surgions, and Apothecaries, would fill a ſeuerall and great Volume. I will onely point at one vulgar and common Fault, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hindering the happy proceeding, and ſucceeding of our Cures in London. And that is the fickleneſſe, and fugitiue Inconſtancie of our Patients, who being perſwaded by euery pratling Goſſip that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in to ſee them, and ſilly Chare-woman that attendeth them, will haue for euery Day they are ſicke almoſt, a new and ſeuerall Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and perhaps chaunge euery Day for the worſe. Thus doo they deli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iari and play the Wantons becauſe of their eaſe and plentie of water at their Doores (I meane the varietie of good and skilfull Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions) but chiefly by the fond and witleſſe motions, of theſe buſie giddy headed women, who are conſtant in nothing but Inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, blowne too and fro with euery breath, like a Feather. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they will diſpraiſe and debaſe the former Phiſition, for no other reaſon, but becauſe hee is knowne vnto them: and magnifie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend a ſtraunger becauſe he is vnknowne, as a man of deepe learning and Iudgement. Otherwhile the Phiſition is too young, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth Experience: and then they will extoll to the Patient, a blinde Empericke, who hath neither Wit, Learning, nor Experience, and yet hee muſt be the Man. Sometime againe the Phyſition is too old, and ſpent, his Memorie and Iudgement faileth him, hee is now done, you muſt take an other that is more freſh and readie in his Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>With theſe and the like, idle, trifleling and childiſh Follyes they do often inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urbe and hinder our Curations: and the Phyſitions are blamed, traduced, and diſgraced, when the Patient himſelfe, or his wiſe Counſellors deſerued well, much rather to be whipped. <hi>Qui Plures conſulit Medicoes in ſingulorum Errorem cadit, ipſe falſus maxime.</hi> He that runneth after many Phiſitions, oft times deceiueth them all, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf moſt &amp; worſt of all. That externall Euents do interrupt the courſe of Curation, and daſh all on the ſudden. it is moſt euident. A Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in London had a Patient, who hauing bene ſicke of a burning Feuer, and beeing in good way of recouerie, a Creditor of his (to whome hee owed a round ſumme, hearing of his Sickneſſe, and daunger, preſſed ſuddenly into the Chamber where hee lay, and expoſtulating with him, in many ſharpe, and rigorous words and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21413:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
threats for ſecuritie of his Debt, ſo diſquieted, vexed, and ouerheat the poore Man, that hee relapſed into a Phrenſie and Idleneſſe of Braine, crying out ſtill vpon his Creditor, that he would lay him vp, that the Sergeants were at his backe, readie to ſeize vpon him: that he muſt lye by it, his Wiſe and Children ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: and thus ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, within fewe dayes dyed. This Man might haue recouered in the Phiſitions Iudgement, if this vnhappy Accident had not happened. Incomparable <hi>Galen,</hi> the ſtore-houſe of all good learning, from whoſe reading, the beſt learned ſhall euer returne more learned, concurieth in this point, with his Maiſter <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> as hath bene alreadie by the way touched, and might be by many places of his workes plainely proued, if it were not altogether ſuperfluous, to ſpend Tyme, and blot Paper, in a matter ſo euident. Conſider then, the intollerable &amp; ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Impudencie of our vaunting Pyrgopolynices, who wil take vpon him to ſet <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> to Schoole, as ſimple &amp; rude fellows in reſpect of his graund-Maiſterſhip. And heerein that brain-ſicke Germaine, that notorious Sophiſter, and Impoſtor of the World, <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelſus,</hi> hath plainly diſcouered himſelfe to be a mere <hi>Mounte-banke:</hi> (for if he had bene a learned Man, he would neuer haue done it) bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king euery where in his rouing and rauing Diſcourſes (for Method or Art they haue none in them) at <hi>Galen,</hi> one of the Springs of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, chalenging himſelfe for Ignorance, his Medicines for inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie, and inualiditie: all his Succeſſors and Followers in the Phyſick Schooles and Vniuerſities, for Dolts, Dunſes, and Aſſes, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his goodly Selfe. <hi>Ebrius est nec enim faceret haec ſobrius Vnquam.</hi> The Wine was in, and the Wit was out, when hee did and ſpake this, or elſe vndoubtedly he would neuer haue done it. But to let him goe, into whoſe groſſe, and palpable Abſurdities, intollerable Inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and incredible Sophiſtications, if a man ſhould enter, he ſhould find <hi>Powles</hi> work, as we ſay: it is more then manifeſt, both by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, and ſound Reaſons of theſe graue and learned Phiſitions, to whom, theſe baſe Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions are not worthy to hold the Candle, or to be Named the ſame yeare with them, that all Diſeaſes are not Cure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; and that therefore they are notorious, and not ſufferable Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, who take vpon them, more then the greateſt Maiſters of Art would euer arrogate to Themſelues; and that which indeed is not in their power to performe. The like may be ſaid of Cures, which was ſaid of Martiall affaires. <hi>In rebus bellicis, Militum virtus, locorum oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitas, Claſſes, Comeatus, Auxilia, multum tuuant, Qnin ipſa. Rerum Domina Fortuna magnam partem ſuo ſibi Iuro vindicat, &amp;c.</hi> So in Curati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21413:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Skilfulneſſe, and Carefulneſſe of the Phyſition, the Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Tractabilitie of the Patient, and diligence of the Keepers and Attendants, the faithfulneſſe of the Apothecaries, Surgions, and other Miniſters, the remouing of all externall Impediments, do greatly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and forward Curations: but aboue all, and when all is done, there is a great Commaunder who ſitteth in Heauen, and chalengeth to himſelf by good right, the chiefe ſway and ſtroke in all this Buſineſſe. In him are the iſſues of Life, and of Death, he hath created both Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke and the Phyſition. <hi>Quo ſine Diptamnus nil, Panacea iuuat.</hi> Except the Lord build the Houſe, the builders, &amp;c. Except the Lord watch the Citie, the Watch-men, &amp;c. The Eternall who hath giuen vs theſe Soules and Bodies, (of whom it ſhould ſeeme theſe iolly fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, theſe boaſting Thraſoes do fildome, or neuer thinke) hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to himſelfe a ſoueraigne and ouerruling Power: whereby hee doth oft times croſſe the Meanes, and fruſtrate the Hopes of the moſt skilfull and exquiſit Artiſts, much more, of our bold Periclirators, who blindly, ſottiſhly, and ſenceleſly, go to worke. This cauſed that Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſed old Man, whoſe Fame is like to laſt as long as the World laſteth, cry out, that there was <hi>Diuinum quid in morbis,</hi> a certaine Miſterie in Diſeaſes, which neither he, nor any humane Wit could euer ſound.</p>
            <p>Their next Topicall Place, or perſwaſiue Inſinuation pretending the Patients good, is this, that as they vndertake without all perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture, an abſolute Cure, be the Diſeaſe neuer ſo ſtubborne or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious; ſo they likewiſe promiſe with no leſſe Impudence and Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, a ſhort and ſpeedie Cure. This is exceeding plauſible to the poore Patient, bringing him a ſleepe, and cauſing him to ſcratch where it itcheth not. He will (forſooth) leap ouer the hedge before he come at it: he will not ſtand thrumming of Caps, or picking ſtrawes all the yeare, but with great Celeritie &amp; Dexteritie, diſpatch that in a weeke, which the Rationall Phyſition, the Schoole-Doctor with his Caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Caueats, will lye bungling and iumbling at a Moneth or two. Yet the wiſe Man willeth vs to haſten ſlowly, and telleth vs that a ſoft fire maketh ſweete Mault, that a Thing is done ſoone inough, if wel inough: that haſtie Bitches bring forth blinde Whelpes: that raſh Temeritie is the Daughter of Folly, and Mother of Repentance. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Diſeaſes proceeding from Inanition and Exhauſtion, require ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, a conuenient ſpace of Tyme, that Natures loſſe and expence may be by degrees repaired, reſtored, and (as it were) reedified. Others are of a Churliſh, Stubbborne, and Rebellious Diſpoſition, and muſt be gently and ſoftly handled, and by litle, and litle, in ſome length
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21413:26"/>
of Tyme, tamed and cicurated. They are like a ſleeping Dogge which muſt not ſudenly be awaked, leaſt you do <hi>Irritare Crabronem, duplicare malum,</hi> and bring an old houſe vpon your owne, (or at leaſt) the Patients Head. <hi>Rome</hi> was not built in a Day, and no Matter of waight or moment, can be negotiated and managed in a moment or trice, vnleſſe we will huddle, and ſlubber them vp in ſuch ſort, as we muſt doo, redoo, vndoo, and as good neuer a whit, as neuer the better.</p>
            <p>Their laſt and ſureſt Card, whereby as with a cunning &amp; ſtrong Engine, they breake open the Gates of the long aſſayled Fort, making themſelues Lord, and Owners thereof, ſo as the poore Patient dooth yeeld himſelfe as altogether vanquiſhed and ſubdued, and not able, to hold out any longer, is this. They will ſolemnly profeſſe, that though their skill be ſingular, and ſupereminent, yet their Deſire is rather to doo Good, then to heape vp Gold: (for if they had bene of that humour, they might haue bene worth thouſands, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>umbled themſelues in ſiluer before this time) and therfore for the good liking they conceiue of the Patient, and his gentle and courteous Nature and behauiour, they will require nothing, vntill they haue performed, and perfited the Cure. Herevpon the Patient is ſo well appayed, that he thinketh he hath gotten the Popes holowneſſe by the Toe, &amp; met with the plaineſt, kindeſt, honeſteſt, and friendlyeſt Gentleman in the World. But you muſt know, that though our craftie Copſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, and old beaten Veterator, gloze, and glauer thus, yet hee meaneth nothing leſſe. For hauing by this meanes entered into worke with the Patient, after three, or foure Dayes, all which while, he will ſhewe himſelfe double Diligent, and tell him many a fayre Tale, and loud Leſing, hee will (ſpying his opportunitie) breake with him thus.</p>
            <p>(Syr) you diſcerne (I hope) that I haue a ſpeciall care of you, you ſee what continuall paines I take, beſide the expence and laying out of my money out of my purſe for your Medicines. I truſt you will haue ſome conſideration hereof, and allow me money for to pay the Apothecarie. The Patient (if he be of any good, or kinde Nature, being ouercome with kindneſſe) cannot but yeeld to this equall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and vſually wil out with his purſe, and giue him foure or fiue An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, to buy Poticary Ware, as they vſe to ſpeake. This our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Mounte-banke</hi> receiueth with a right good will, ſaying to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that hee ſhall not now looſe all, but that hee is reaſonable well payde for fiue or ſixe, or at moſt tenne ſhillings beſtowed in Drugges
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21413:26"/>
And for the moſt part, when they haue gotten poſſeſſion of this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, they haue attained the end and toppe of theyr drifts. For you muſt vnderſtand, that the greateſt part of them tarry not out the proceſſe of theyr Cures. But hauing made foure or fiue ſuch like Markets in ſeuerall places of the Towne, wherevnto they arriue, they betake themſelues faire and roundly to their heeles, giuing theyr Patients the bagge, and leauing them in the lurch, in the middeſt of their Foole-conceited Hopes.</p>
            <p>And although I might ſay, <hi>His facient exemola fidem,</hi> for Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of theſe notorious Couzenages doo abound, and are too plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all Places, yet becauſe I feare leaſt I haue tarried too long in this baſe Argument, and ſpent too much time in ſtirring this filthy Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, I will haſten to an ende, and exemplifie my Diſcourſe with one onely Store.</p>
            <p>That baſe, vnlettered, and vnmannered Thick-skin, (of whom mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the way was formerly made, <hi>B.</hi> of <hi>H.</hi> by the Thames ſide) comming to London, and noyſing abroad by his Trumpettors, his ſingular and admirable Skill and Dexteritie in curing diuers daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, deſperate, and in truth, incurable Diſeaſes, was brought by ſome of his Brokers, to a graue and honeſt Cittizen, afflicted with that Maladie, wherein the learned Phyſitions flye to <hi>Solus Culter, Solus Cultellus.</hi> This noble Swanne, this vaine and vaunting Clowne, bragging of ſundrie great and wonderfull Cures by him performed vpon Gentlemen and others in the Countrey, whom he bluſhed not to name, knowing that the Parties being abſent, he could not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolled, profeſſed to cure him abſolutely (without cutting) and that in three weekes ſpace. The Cittizen though hee gaue too liſtening an eare to theſe goodly Tales of our cracking <hi>Mounte-banke,</hi> and was ſomewhat tickled to heare of Health and Recouery, and that with ſuch celeritie and expedition, yet hauing a tollerable and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of a Phiſition, whom formerly he vſed, ſent vnto him, deſiring him to conferre with our deepe and profound Artiſt, &amp; to ioyne with him in the Curation. The Phyſition repayring to the Patients houſe, and entering Parlee with our <hi>Mounſier Magnifico, Signior Rusticus,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted him to know what Courſe he would take in the Cure. I (quoth he) will giue him no Phyſicke. How will you then (replyed the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition) remoue the Diſeaſe. I will do it (ſaith our Quack-ſaluer) by a certaine Gift giuen mee, and by a rare and precious ſecret Medicine which I vſe.</p>
            <p>No maruel (anſwered the Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) if your Medicine being no Phiſick,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21413:27"/>
be ſtraunge and rare indeed aboue all I euer heard. But will you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and ſhewe your Medicine, that wee may diſcerne and Iudge of the fitneſſe and efficacie thereof, to performe this great and ſtrange effect. Nay by your leaue (ſaid hee) you ſhall pardon me, the foole is wiſer then ſo. If I would haue diſcouered my Secret, two great Doctors of <hi>Oxford</hi> would haue aſſured me an Annuitie of fortie pound yearely, during my life. I am ſufficiently knowne I tell you (Syr) and that to no Babes, or baſe Perſons, but to diuers of the greateſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen in the Land: and am admitted to their Speech and Preſence, when Veluet Coates daunce attendance without. The Phiſition per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing by this ſmall Conference, <hi>Mounſier Mounte-banke</hi> to bee of the right ſtampe, taking the Patient aſide, and ſhewing him the groſſe Ignorance, and intollerable Arrogancie of the Sottiſh Aſſe, perſwaded him in many words, to ſhake him off, if he reſpected his Life, Health, or Credit, as a meere Couzener and Impoſtor. But he (though otherwiſe of ſufficient wiſedome) was ſo inueigled, or rather bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the great bragges, and ſenceleſſe Tales of this braggadoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Quack-ſaluer, that he would admit of nothing ſounding to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, or Diſparagement: affirming that by dealing with him, he could receiue no detriment, ſince hee required no money, vntill he had ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued and finiſhed his Cure. The Phyſition anſwered, that though hee made that goodly pretence to drawe him on, and himſelfe into the Cure, yet it was like, that by one meanes or other hee would get into poſſeſſion, ſome peece of mony (for ſure hee was, that was the whyte and marke hee aymed at) and then bidde him farewell. This proued afterwards a very ſhrewd and perillous Prediction. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in fewe Dayes, paſſing by the Citizens Houſe, he called in, to ſee how the world went, and was by him ſaluted thus. (Syr) I doubt you will proue a Prophet, my Cunning Man, the laſt Day, complaining that he layed out his money at the Apothecaries, to buy Simples to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound my Medicines, I thinking it no reaſon hee ſhould bee at ſuch charge for me, opened my Purſe, and gaue him foure Angels. But I haue wiſhed them ſince twiſe in it againe: for I feare hee will make your words good, he hath caſt me once or twiſe by his tamperings and Drugges, into the fit of an Ague, ſo that I was readie (but for ſhame) to haue ſent for you. I beleeue, when all is done, hee will ſhewe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Couzening Companion. The Phyſition ſmyling, anſwered: who then I perceiue your deepe Doctor will not looſe all his labour. He hath now as much money as he will looke for at your hands, and you as much Good, as you muſt expect from his. Hee hath cleared
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21413:27"/>
three Angels at the leaſt, (ſheare gaines) for three or foure Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: which if you had giuen the moſt learned Phiſition in the Citie, you would haue ſcratched your Elbow, and thought your ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. Yet he fayled in his firſt conceit, which notwithſtanding is commonly their Reſt. For not long after the ſhameleſſe Companion faigned a neceſſary and vrgent occaſion of going into the Countrey, and before he went down, deſired to haue ſo much of thoſe Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities wherein his Patient dealt, as came to three Pound. The Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen knowing that by his meanes he had got in the Citie of diuers ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Men through his Hyberbolicall Commendation, twentie No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles at the leaſt, was content to lay them aſide for him. But when he expected his preſent payment, he phopped him thus. Syr, we agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for your Cure for fiue pound. I haue receiued alreadie fortie ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: now this three pound maketh vp the iuſt ſumme. Nay by your leaue (ſaid the Marchant) I looke for readie money for my Ware. You haue had on me alreadie foure Angels, and I am no whit better then I was, but rather in worſe State. Performe your vndertaken Cure, and you ſhall be aſſured of your money without faile. If it be ſo (ſaid hee) I muſt leaue it behinde me til I return or ſend you vp money: for I haue ſent downe my money before me. But neither Man nor Mony retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in haſte. This was an old-beaten Souldier, a good Proficient, well trained vp in this Schoole of Couzenage, and Coney-catching, hee had learned his leſſon perfectly, and was able to runne it ouer vpon his fingers Ends. For if you compare his Story with our preſent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, you ſhall ſee that he neither failed nor faltered in any one Point of his Portuſe.</p>
            <p>Thus I haue ſpent (as you ſee) ſome fewe ſucceſſiue and Idle-vagant houres, in vnfolding and laying open the Packe and Fardle of theſe circumferanious Iuglers, and pedling Pettifoggers in Phyſicke, who by theſe Adulterate, and Sophſticate Wares, deceiue, abuſe, pray, and feed vpon the ruder and ſimpler ſort of People. Yea, and by your leaue, ſometimes ouerreach &amp; circumue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thoſe, who think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues iolly fellowes, and great wiſe Men, to the great blemiſh and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of that auncient, worthy, and honourable Profeſſion of Phyſick, diſcredit, obloquie, and contempt of learned and good Phiſitions, and to the great damage and detriment of her Maieſties Subiects, both in their Bodies, and outward Eſtates. My hope is, that this Curſorie, and Rapſodicall Diſcourſe (for to haue ranſacked euery Corner and Creuiſe in this Budget, would require a longer Tractat, and may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be performed if this (Labor) proue plauſible and grateful may do
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21413:28"/>
good to ſome, and hurt none, except the intruding and shifting <hi>Mounte-banke,</hi> whoſe proſequution, and perſequution, both I, and all the learned Gentlemen of our Colledge, haue in our Initiation and Inanguratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolemnly vowed, and proteſted. It being the very ground and Originall, of all thoſe large and bountifull Immunities and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges graunted firſt to our Societie, by that puiſſant Prince of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous memorie, <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, and afterward ratified and confirmed by his Peerleſſe Daughter, Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Mirrour of all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roicall and Princely vertues, the Aſſertor and Protector of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Maule of Antichriſt, the Aſtoniſhment and Wonder of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, and the whole World, that we ſhould, <hi>Videre &amp; prospicere, ne quid in Rebus Med. Resp. Detrimenti caperet.</hi> That is, that we ſhould foreſee and take order, that the Common-wealth be not wronged in Matters appertaining to Phiſicke. It is therefore an odious Calumnie, and ſlaunderous vntruth, which theſe baſe and out-caſt Companions giue out, when they are puniſhed by the Colledge, for theyr groſſe Sottiſhneſſe, ſhameleſſe Intruſion, and vnſufferable, and pernicious Offences and Diſorders, that they are therefore onely purſued by vs, becauſe they take away our profit, (when as in truth, they eft-ſoones make worke for vs) and doo more good, then the Colledge of Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: whereas the great Acts they do, may appeare partly by this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſcourſe, and yet more euidently by thoſe lamentable Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and miſerable Ends of many poore ſoules in London in a yeare, falling into theſe Hucſters, or rather Hackſters hands. Our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences toward God, our Dutie toward our Prince, our Loue to our Countrey, the honour of our Profeſſion, the Oath we haue taken in our Admiſſion, do all binde vs, as by a double or triple cord or band, <hi>Ad perſequendum indoctos Empericos, &amp; Impoſtores.</hi> To purſue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Emperickes, and Impoſtors.</p>
            <p>In concluſion therefore, I deſire them who haue occaſion to vſe Phyſicke, to remember alwayes his ſaying, who affirmeth, that <hi>Plus mali a medico quam a Morbo imminet, ſi aut audacia, aut Imperitia Poccet.</hi> There is more Daunger to bee feared from the Phyſition, then from the Diſeaſe, if he offend either in blockiſh Ignorance, or raſh Temeritie; and thinke it ſafe for them, to be of the ſame minde with a great Learned Clarke in our Land, who in a daungerous ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, being moued by ſome friends to vſe an vnlettered Empericke. Nay (quoth he) I haue liued all my Life by the Booke, and I will now (God-willing) likewiſe dye by the Booke. And ſo I wiſh from my heart to euery one of them, in Tyme of Health, a ſound, faithfull, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21413:28"/>
conſtant friend, who is called <hi>Medicamentum vitae,</hi> and that they may auoyd the Silken and Oylye Tongues of the flattering Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, and in Time of Sickneſſe, an honeſt and learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: and that they may not fall into the butcherly hands of the mercileſſe Carnifex (I would but (becauſe it is out, and not amiſſe, let it goe) haue ſaid) Quack-ſaluer.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Carpere vel noli Nostra, veledae Tua.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <p>Diuers faults haue eſcaped the Printer; which as they are eaſily diſcerned. ſo I entreat thee (friendly Reader) to amend with thy Pen, as thou goest along: and to pardon me, who by occaſion of ſome Buſineſſe, haue not looked ſo narrowly to them, as I ſhould, and (otherwiſe) would haue done.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
